<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The healing attempt examined and submitted to the Parliament convocation whether it be healing or hurtful to the peace of the church.</title>
            <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49116</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26161</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09375064</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09375064</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42888</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49116)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42888)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1311:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The healing attempt examined and submitted to the Parliament convocation whether it be healing or hurtful to the peace of the church.</title>
                  <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Freeman Collins and are to be sold by Richard Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed and entred according to order."</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Long--NUC pre-l956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42888:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Healing Attempt <hi>Examined and Submitted</hi>
               </hi> TO THE PARLIAMENT AND CONVOCATION, Whether it be HEALING or HURTFUL To the Peace of the CHURCH.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOB XXIV. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Some remove the Land-marks, they violently take away the Flocks, and feed thereof.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed and Entred according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Freeman Collins,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Richard Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old-Bailey.</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42888:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42888:2"/>
            <head>THE Healing Attempt EXAMINED, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Author begins with his Bleſſing. And without Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, a good Conceit therefore he ſeems to have of himſelf, who attempts to impoſe his Conceptions on the Judgment of thoſe Thirty Divines, to whom he preſents them, and to perſwade them to Aboliſh that Government and Liturgy, to which they have obliged themſelves to live in Obedience and Conformity by their Oaths and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions. And immediately to his Bleſſing, he ſubjoyns what implies a Curſe, for loading and increaſing the Burthens of their Non-conforming Brethren, though he ſeems to excuſe it, as being done againſt their wills. And gives it, as the Belief of his Brethren, <hi>That no good will be done them by that Meeting or Convocation,</hi> ſeeing they ſay, <hi>it is impoſſible that they,</hi> &amp;c. How this ſhould ſtimulate them to a greater earneſtneſs to do what they believe and have made impoſſible to be done, I cannot ſee; nor can the Author conceive, ſeeing he thinks it unneceſſary to propound any other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument than what is contained in the Title <hi>(i. e.)</hi> Such a Moderation of Epiſcopacy, that the Power be kept within the line of our firſt Reformers, which will certainly deſtroy his Project, and confirm the preſent Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to Epiſcopacy and Liturgy, from the ſtrict impoſition whereof he hopes to be freed. The Author complains of want of time and ſearch, to excuſe the ſlenderneſs of his Attempt: But if Mr. <hi>Jo. Humphryes</hi> be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, I ſuppoſe he hath had ſufficient time ſince his renouncing his re-ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was about Twenty Years ſince; and that he had made his ſearch before, he with the help of other his Non-Con-Brethren, ſet forth their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to the Defence of Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> wherein the chiefeſt of his preſent Arguments were then urged, and ſhortly after refuted, as by the following Account will hereafter appear.</p>
            <p>He tells his Readers, <hi>That it is impoſſible for the Diſſenters to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite,</hi> if it be ſtill affirmed, <hi>That the Biſhop and Presbyters are not of the ſame Order, That the Power of Ordination is the ſole Prerogative of the Biſhops</hi> (i.e.) <hi>if the Presbyters may not Ordain as effectually as the Biſhops; That the Ordination by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42888:3"/>Presbyters only is void, That the Ordaining them again by Biſhops is not re-ordination.</hi> This, ſaith our Author, deſtroys the Church-ſtate, not only of the Diſſenters, but of all other Proteſtants in the World; which is a very large ſtretch, ſeeing there are many other Proteſtant Churches, who affirm and practice the ſame things with the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and yet he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, <hi>That if a comprehenſion may not be had but on theſe terms, there can be none at all.</hi> However, ſeeing he makes his Appeal to the Sentiments of the firſt Reformers in the days of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. <hi>Edward</hi> VI. and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to them we will joyntly ſubmit, becauſe he ſays, <hi>that will heal our Diviſions touching Church Government;</hi> of which I doubt, ſeeing I have Reaſon to ſay, they are not impartially propoſed by Mr. <hi>J.H.</hi> nor will be found to be ſo exactly the ſame with the Diſſenters. So that if the preſent Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy appear to be the ſame as it was in the days of the firſt Reformers, Martyrs, and Confeſſors, and our Liturgy much more Reformed, though they accounted it ſuch a Grievance, as neither they nor their Fathers could bear.</p>
            <p>Their Non Conformity will ſtill lye under the interpretation of a peeviſh Humour and Obſtinacy, though they do with the like Confidence pretend, that they have Antiquity as well as our firſt Reformers on their ſide; it is a condeſcention in the Author to acknowledge, that the Canons of <hi>James</hi> I. run another way, and to thoſe Canons the Clergy did conſent, as do the preſent Clergy; and if, as he ſays, Arch-Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> adhered to the firſt Reformers, we may yet hope for an Accommodation. As for the Opinions of particular Divines, I ſhall refer them to their due place, and only intimate his Obſervation to the Reader, That becauſe Juriſdiction is given to the Dean and Chapter of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> during the Suſpenſion of the Arch-Biſhop, therefore they have alſo the Power of conferring Orders, when other Deans and Arch-Deacons alſo have an Epiſcopal Juriſdiction in their ſeveral pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liars, but neither of them have the Power of Orders; and <hi>fruſtra eſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia quae nunquam reducitur in actum.</hi> And St. <hi>Hierom</hi> expreſly appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates Ordination to the Biſhops only.</p>
            <p>As to Mr. <hi>Clerkson</hi>'s Excellent Diſcourſe of Liturgies, I ſhall recommend to the Reader's peruſal, what hath been written by Biſhop <hi>Taylor,</hi> Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Faulkner,</hi> to which I may add Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Epiſtle to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, and leave it to the Reader's determination, whether a Liturgy of Extemporary Prayers are moſt agreeable to Publick Worſhip.</p>
            <p>I agree with the Author in his Introduction, <hi>That our Diviſions had too great a hand in bringing us under thoſe Dangers, and keeping us in thoſe Fears which are ſtill threatning us;</hi> but that Indulgence and Comprehenſion toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will ſecure us, I much doubt, becauſe Experience hath taught the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; and therefore, though Mr. <hi>J. H.</hi> apprehends a neceſſity, for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of many thouſand Souls, to let in Men of more tender Conſciences <hi>(Abſit invidia)</hi> to ſet open the Church-Doors wider, I think it may be a means to let in many Adverſaries with a few Friends. I know the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of Diſſenters have been bold and clamourous ever ſince the Reign of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42888:3"/>Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and great boaſts made of their Numbers, and never louder than in the days of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt of Bleſſed Memory, where the Martial Canons were planted to throw down the Eccleſiaſtical, and the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of Diſſenters worried that Good Prince and the Archbiſhop out of their Lives; and therefore I think our Governours, both in Church and State, had more juſt cauſe to complain of the Diſſenters, than theſe of them; whereof you ſhall hear a fuller account from thoſe whom the Author mentioneth, as Friends to his new Model. As to the Quotation from Sir <hi>Robert Cotton,</hi> I cannot much commend the ingenuity of Mr. <hi>J. H.</hi> who in the midſt of it leaves out theſe words, (after theſe words)—<hi>Duty to their Sovereign:</hi> It thus proceeds: <hi>Therewith ſtart up from among us ſome that might have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended for their Zeal, if it had been tempered with Diſcretion; who fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>running the Authority of the Magiſtrate, took upon them in ſundry places, and publickly to cenſure what agreed not with their private conceits; with which groſs humours, vented in Pulpits and Pamphlets, moſt Men grew to be frozen in Zeal,</hi> &amp;c. And the Marginal Note ſays, <hi>Some think, that if theſe Mens zeal had by order been put to imploy it ſelf otherwiſe, and a task ſet them to do ſome good and memorable thing in the Church, they might have been reformed or made harmleſs by diverſion.</hi> I deſire Mr. <hi>J. H.</hi> to conſider what it is, and of whom Sir <hi>Robert</hi> there ſpeaketh, and to give a Reaſon why this was interpoled. And to this Quotation I ſhall ſubjoyn another of Mr. <hi>R. B</hi>'s in an Epiſtle to his ſeparated Brethren, <hi>That thouſands are gone to Hell, and ten thouſands going after them; who would never have gone thither, if they had kept in the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their Pariſh-Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the concluſion of the Introduction, he ſeems no way ſatisfied with the Propenſion of our Governours to lay aſide the ſtrict uſe of Ceremonies, and other more offenſive Impoſitions, unleſs this one thing may be granted; and, I think, ſuch a grant will be ſtill accounted a grievance, <hi>(viz.)</hi> a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the Government of the Church to be no other than what it was held and intended by the firſt Reformers; in the mean time he avers, That that Government which is really eſtabliſhed by Law, is not only inconſiſtent with, and deſtructive of that which was ſetled in the Church by the firſt Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, but of the Church-ſtate of all other Proteſtants. This <hi>Durus Sermo.</hi> This is his endeavour as to the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth in his firſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter.</p>
            <p>Here I think fit to advertiſe the Reader, that the Materials for the new Model of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's Biſhops, was fitted (though Mr. <hi>J. H.</hi> complains for want of time) above ſeven years ſince, and the Scheme drawn-up by Mr. <hi>H.</hi> in's half Sheet, and offered to a Parliament; and becauſe he took no notice of what was then ſaid in Anſwer to his Model, in a Tract called, <hi>No Proteſtant, but the Diſſenters Plot,</hi> Printed 1682. He deſerves to do Pennance in a whole Sheet now; and becauſe that Anſwer may be after ſo many years become forgotten; or rarely found; I beg the Reader's leave to repeat ſo much of it as concerns the State of our Church, and the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Divines that then lived as to Epiſcopacy; becauſe our Author
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42888:4"/>ſays the whole ſtreſs of his cauſe upon it; ſaying, <hi>That this one thing is the moſt effectual expedient in the whole World, to promote his healing attempt;</hi> wherein I ſhall joyn iſſue with him. It might be expected, that he ſhould have laid a ſure and ſolid Corner-ſtone for his new Model, becauſe an error in the foundation doth uſually run through the whole Fabrick; but this will appear to be nothing elſe but Slime and Sand; that is, in plain Engliſh, a confident Impoſture and Fiction of his own Brain; for, <hi>p.</hi> 9. the account which this Author gives of that excellent Book, <hi>The Erudition of a Chriſtian Man,</hi> is this, <hi>That of theſe two Orders only,</hi> (viz.) <hi>Prieſts and Deacons, Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture makes expreſs mention, and how they were conferred by the Apoſtles by Prayer and Impoſition of hands.</hi> Thus ſaith Mr. <hi>H. There are but two Orders only,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Prieſts and Deacons, no third Order; Biſhops therefore muſt be of the ſame Order with Prieſts.</hi> And again, <hi>That all ſuch lawful Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therity of any one Biſhop,</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> adds, in a Parentheſis (or Prieſt, for they are in the ſenſe of theſe great Divines the ſame) <hi>over another were, and be given them by the Conſent, Ordinance, and poſitive Laws of Men, and not by any Ordinance of God in Holy Scripture.</hi> So far the neceſſary Erudition. Now that there may be a fair trial of this caſe, I ſhall ſet down from Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s printed Paper, the Opinions of thoſe Divines which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted about our Reformation in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's days: concerning which I ſhall only mind the Diſſenters of an Obſervation of their own, <hi>viz. That though ſome of theſe Reformers were of different Opinions as to ſome Points mentioned in this Manuſcript, yet they muſt be conſidered to have receded from them when they ſubſcribed the</hi> Neceſſary Erudition, <hi>being then all of that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is there deſcribed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The intent of Printing Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Manuſcript, containing the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the Archbiſhop and ſeveral Biſhops and Divines of ſome Queſtions concerning the Sacraments, was, as Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> ſays, that it might appear with what maturity and care they proceeded in the Reformation. And the Subſcriptions which were at the end of every mans Paper, he tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 242. were in this form: T. Cant. <hi>This is my Opinion and Sentence; which I do not temerariouſly define, but do remit the Judgment thereof wholly to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi>— and as is alſo ſometimes expreſſed, <hi>p.</hi> 201. <hi>without prejudice to the Truth, and ſaving always more better Judgment:</hi> Cum facultate etiam me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius deliberandi in hac parte. Now this Conſultation was ſome years before the Book was publiſhed; and if any of the Biſhops had been then of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Opinion, as the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> obſerve that Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> was in the caſe of Excommunication, inclining to <hi>Eraſtianiſm,</hi> from theſe they muſt be conſidered (ſay the <hi>Diſſenters</hi>) to have receded, becauſe they ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition;</hi> p. 8. This Manuſcript ſpeaks home to our purpoſe in</p>
            <p>Queſt. 9. <hi>Whether the Apoſtles lacking a higher power, as in not having a a Chriſtian King among them, made Biſhops by that neceſſity, or by authority given by God?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42888:4"/>
            <p>The Anſwer of the Archbiſhop to this Queſtion, as indeed to many others, is ſingular, and differs from the reſt of the Reformers; being, as the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facers</hi> themſelves do obſerve, meer <hi>Eraſtianiſm,</hi> p. 7. but from theſe alſo (as they ſay of his Opinion concerning Excommunication, <hi>p.</hi> 8.) he muſt be conſidered to have receded, becauſe he ſubſcribed the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition;</hi> which being done on more mature deliberation, we ought to impute nothing to the Archbiſhop as his judgment in thoſe controverted Points, but what is there by him aſſerted. I ſhall therefore mention the Reſolutions of the reſt only as we find them in the Re-collection; only of this firſt I ſhall ſpeak at large.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>York.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>We find in SS. that the Apoſtles uſed the power to make</hi> Biſhops, Prieſts, <hi>and</hi> Deacons; <hi>which power may be grounded upon theſe words:</hi> Sicut miſit me vivens Pater, ſic ego mitto vos. <hi>And we verily think that they durſt not have uſed ſo high a power, unleſs they had had authority from Chriſt. But that their power to ordain Biſhops, Prieſts, or Deacons by Impoſition of hands, requireth any other authority than authority of God, we neither read in SS. nor out of SS.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>London</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I think the Apoſtles made Biſhops by the Law of God, becauſe</hi> Acts 22. <hi>it is ſaid,</hi> In quo vos Spiritus Sanctus poſuit. <hi>Nevertheleſs I think if Chriſtian Princes had been then, they ſhould have named by Right, and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſaid Biſhops to their places.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſter.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I think that the Apoſtles made Biſhops by authority given them from God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Carliſle.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Chriſt made his Apoſtles Prieſts and Biſhops, and that he gave them power to make others, it ſeemeth to be the very Trade of SS.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Robertſon.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I think the Apoſtles made Biſhops and Presbyters by divine authority, where the publick Magiſtrate did permit it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Cox.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Although the Apoſtles had no authority to force any man to be Prieſts, yet (they moved by the Holy Ghoſt) had authority of God to exhort and induce men to ſet forth God's honour, and ſo to make them Prieſts.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Day.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Apoſtles ordained Biſhops by authority given them by God.</hi> Joh. 20. Sicut miſit me, &amp;c. Item Joh. ult. &amp; Acts 20. &amp; 1 Tim. 4. Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ordinavit Timotheum &amp; Titum, &amp; preſcribit quales ille debeant ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare, 1 Tim. 1. Tit. 1.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Oglethorp.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Apoſtles by authority and command of God, did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain and inſtitute Biſhops, leave being deſired and obtained from the Prince or Magiſtrate who was then chief. As I ſuppoſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Redman.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt gave his Apoſtles authority to make Biſhops and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in his Church, as he had received authority of the Father to make them Biſhops. But if any Chriſtian Prince had then been, the Apoſtles had been and ought to have been obedient Subjects, and would have attempted nothing but under the permiſſion and aſſent of their earthly Governours. Yet was it meet that they which were ſpecial and elect Servants of our Saviour Chriſt, and were ſent by him to convert the World, and having most abundantly the Holy Ghoſt in them, ſhould have ſpecial ordering of ſuch Miniſtry as pertained to the plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42888:5"/>and increaſing of the Faith: whereunto I doubt not but a Christian Prince of his godly mind would most lovingly have condeſcended. And it is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in this Question, with other like, this word</hi> making <hi>a Biſhop or Priest, may be taken two ways: for underſtanding the word to</hi> ordain <hi>or</hi> conſecrate, <hi>ſo it is a thing which pertaineth to the Apoſtles and their Succeſſours only; but but if by this word</hi> (making) <hi>be underſtood the</hi> appointing <hi>or</hi> naming <hi>to the Office, ſo it pertaineth ſpecially to the ſupreme Heads and Governours of the Church, which be Princes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Edgworth.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Apoſtles made Biſhops and Prieſts by authority given them of God, and not for lack of any higher power: notwithſtanding, where there is a Chriſtian King or Prince, the Election, Deputation, and Aſſignation of them that ſhall be Prieſts and Biſhops, belongeth to the King or Prince, ſo that he may forbid any Biſhop within his Kingdom that he give no Orders, for conſiderations moving him; and may aſſign him a time when he ſhall give Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and to whom: Example of King</hi> David, 1 Chron. 24. <hi>dividing the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites into</hi> twenty four Orders, <hi>deputing over every Order one chief Biſhop; preſcribing an Ordinal and Rule how they ſhould do their duties and courſes; and what Sacrifices, Rites and Ceremonies they ſhould uſe every day, as the day and time required. And his Son King</hi> Solomon <hi>diligently executed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the ſame uſages to be obſerved in the Temple, after he had erected and finiſhed it,</hi> 2 Chron. 8.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Symmons.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Apoſties made Biſhops and Prieſts by authority given them of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Treſham.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Apoſtles had authority of God to make Biſhops: yet if there had been a Chriſtian King in any place where they made Biſhops, they would and ought to have deſired authority of him for the executing of ſuch God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acts; which no Chriſtian King would have denied.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Leighton.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Apoſtles, as I ſuppoſe, made Biſhops by authority given to them of Chriſt: howbeit I think they would and ſhould have required the Chriſtian Princes conſent and licenſe thereto, if there had been any Chriſtian Kings or Princes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Coren.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Apoſtles made Biſhops and Prieſts by authority given them of God: Notwithſtanding, if there had been a Chriſtian King at that time, it had been their duties to have had his licenſe and permiſſion thereto.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <p>Here you ſee they all affirm that the Apoſtles, by authority from God, did make Biſhops as well as Prieſts and Deacons; and that there needs no other authority for their Succeſſours to do the like, but what is given them of God. Now that they were diſtinct Orders, will appear by the next Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 10. <hi>Whether Biſhops or Prieſts were firſt? and if the Prieſt were firſt, then the Prieſt made the Biſhop?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Biſhop of St. <hi>Davids,</hi> my Lord elect of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Dr. <hi>Cox,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Redman</hi> ſay, That <hi>at the beginning they were all One.</hi> The Biſhops of <hi>York, London, Rechester, Carliſle,</hi> Doctors, <hi>Day, Treſham, Symmons, Oglethorp,</hi> be in <hi>other contrary Opinions.</hi> The Biſhop of <hi>York</hi> and Dr. <hi>Treſham</hi> think
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42888:5"/>that <hi>the Apoſtles firſt were Prieſts, and after were made Biſhops, when the overſeeing of other Prieſts was committed to them.</hi> My Lords of <hi>London, Dureſm, Carliſle,</hi> and <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> Drs. <hi>Symmonds</hi> and <hi>Grayford,</hi> think that <hi>the Apoſtles were firſt Biſhops, and they after made other Biſhops and Prieſts.</hi> Drs. <hi>Coren</hi> and <hi>Oglethorp</hi> ſay, That <hi>the Apoſtles were made Biſhops, and the ſeventy two were after made Prieſts.</hi> Dr. <hi>Day</hi> thinks that <hi>Biſhops, as they are now called, were before Prieſts.</hi> My Lord of <hi>London,</hi> Drs. <hi>Edgworth</hi> and <hi>Robertſon,</hi> think it <hi>no inconvenience if a Prieſt made a Biſhop in that time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 11. <hi>Whether a Biſhop hath Authority to make a Prieſt by the SS. or no? and whether any other but onely a Biſhop may make a Prieſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the former part of the Queſtion the Biſhop of St. <hi>Davids</hi> doth anſwer, That <hi>Biſhops have no authority to make Prieſts, unleſs they be authorized of the Chriſtian Prince.</hi> The others do all ſay, <hi>That they be authorized of God.</hi> Yet ſome of them add, <hi>That they cannot uſe their Authority, without their Chriſtian Prince doth permit them.</hi> To the ſecond part, the Anſwer of the Biſhop of St. <hi>Davids is, That Lay-men have otherwhile made Prieſts.</hi> So doth Drs. <hi>Edgworth</hi> and <hi>Redman</hi> ſay, <hi>That</hi> Moſes, <hi>by a priviledge given him of God, made</hi> Aaron <hi>his Brother Prieſt.</hi> Drs. <hi>Treſham, Grayford,</hi> and <hi>Cox,</hi> ſay, That <hi>Lay-men may make Prieſts in time of neceſſity.</hi> The Biſhops of <hi>York, Dureſm, Rocheſter, Carliſle,</hi> Elect of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Drs. <hi>Coren, Leigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Symmonds,</hi> ſeem to deny this thing: for they ſay, <hi>They find not nor read not any ſuch Example.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 12. <hi>Whether in the New Teſtament be required any Conſecration of a Piſhop and Prieſt, or onely appointing to the Office be ſufficient?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Biſhop of St. <hi>Davids</hi> ſaith, <hi>That onely the appointing.</hi> And Dr. <hi>Cox,</hi> That <hi>onely the appointing</hi> cum manuum impoſitione <hi>is ſufficient, without Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration.</hi> The Biſhops of <hi>York, London, Dureſm, Carliſle,</hi> Drs. <hi>Day, Coren, Leighton, Treſham, Edgworth, Oglethorp,</hi> ſay, <hi>That Conſecration is requiſite.</hi> Dr. <hi>Redman</hi> ſaith, <hi>That Conſecration hath been from the Apoſtles time, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted of the Holy Ghoſt, to confer Grace.</hi> My Lord of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> Drs. <hi>Day</hi> and <hi>Symmons</hi> ſay, <hi>The Prieſthood is given</hi> per manuum impoſitionem, <hi>and that by Scripture; and that Conſecration hath of long time been received in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that in this Paper, which contains a previous Conſultation (ſome years before) to the things publiſhed in the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition,</hi> they did general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agree, That the Office of Biſhops is mentioned in Scripture; That they were of a ſuperiour Order to Prieſts; That the Apoſtles made Biſhops by authority from God, and left their Succeſſours power to do the like. And to this they all ſubſcribed in the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much more might be added from ſome publick Writings of that Age, of which I ſhall name but one or two; as firſt, the Book called <hi>Reformatio Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum Eccleſiaſticarum;</hi> a deſign firſt begun by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, as by their two Orders prefixed to that Book, doth appear; and committed to the care of thirty two <hi>Divines</hi> and <hi>Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians,</hi> the Arch-Biſhop being the chief; wherein it is ordered, <hi>That to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42888:6"/>Biſhop all are to give Obedience according to the Word of God,</hi> p. 98. <hi>Epiſcope qui Eccleſiae praeficitur, non ſolum Decanus, Archidiaconus, Archipresbyter, &amp; reliqui Miniſtri parebunt, &amp;c.</hi> And cap. 10. <hi>Epiſcopi, quoniam inter caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros Eccleſiae Miniſtros, locum principem tenent, ideo ſana Doctriná gravi au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate atque provido conſilio debent</hi> inferiores Ordines Cleri <hi>regere ac paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere.</hi> Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> p. 71. of the ſecond part, ſays, <hi>It is plain that</hi> Cranmer <hi>had quite laid aſide thoſe ſingular Opinions which he formerly held of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Functions: for now in a Work of his own, without the concurrence of any other</hi> (ſpeaking of his Catechiſm) <hi>he fully ſets forth their Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I ſhall conſider how agreeable their Deſign is to the Ancient Conſtitution of our Government about matters Eccleſiaſtical, which (as they ſay) is very excellently deſcribed in (the Book called) <hi>The neceſſary Doctrine and Erudition of a Chriſtian-man, compoſed by ſeveral Biſhops and other great Doctors, and approved by Authority in the days of King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth.</hi> The <hi>Diſſenters</hi> cannot have a greater Reverence for that Book than the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> have, as to the Conſtitution of our Church. And to corroborate this Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, they add that of another excellent Book <hi>(viz.) Dr.</hi> Burnet<hi>'s Hiſtory of the Reformation;</hi> for which, as they obſerve, <hi>the whole Kingdom have given the Doctor thanks:</hi> And I ſhall think the worſe of theſe <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> if they will not do the ſame. P. 16. From theſe Books they attempt to prove, that <hi>the eſtabliſhing a Parochial or Congregational Church-Diſcipline</hi> (the great thing which the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> deſire) <hi>may be done conſiſtently with the Ancient Conſtitution of the Government of this Realm, to the fixing the deſired, firm, and laſting <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> P. 11. If this appear, the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> may well boaſt that they are the Genuine Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it was ſetled by the firſt Reformers; and that they have been (as they complain) <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſented as Enemies both to Church and State; as if the adhering to old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Principles about Church-Diſcipline had been the</hi> Overt Act <hi>of a Spirit ſeditious and phanatical,</hi> p. 17. To theſe two they have appealed for the truth of their Aſſertion; and I hope they will not ſhew themſelves ſuch double-minded men, as to be <hi>unſtable in all their ways,</hi> and not ſtand to the Evidence and Arbitration of theſe two Authorities produced by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And if the reducing of us to the Ancient Conſtitution of Church-Government and Diſcipline in this Realm, may fix the deſired, firm, and laſting Union, it will be ſtill the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> fault that we are not all agreed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In that Judicious Tract 'tis manifeſt</hi> (ſay the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> p. 2.)</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That Church-Government is</hi> Jure Divino. Be it ſo.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>That to the conſtituting ſuch a Church-Government, thoſe Church-Officers onely are neceſſary who are mentioned in the New Teſtament.</hi> This is alſo granted.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>That in the New Teſtament there is mention made of no other Church-Officers but Prieſts and Deacons.</hi> This is <hi>ſub judice.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:42888:6"/>
               <item>4. <hi>That Biſhops or Prieſts, the ſole Governours of the Church, are of one and the ſame Order.</hi> This alſo is to be determined.</item>
            </list>
            <p>To all this I ſhall oppoſe a ſhort Syllogiſm, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Church-Government which is mentioned in the New Teſtament (by the Compilers of the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition</hi>) is <hi>Jure Divino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Church Government mentioned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is by Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Church-Government by Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, is <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> according to the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It chanced that on reading this Preface, I had at hand that ancient Book, printed in <hi>Engliſh</hi> 1543. and ſet forth by the King's Authority, as appears by the Preface. I had alſo a Tranſlation of the ſame Book into elegant Latine, printed the following year, <hi>viz.</hi> 1544. This Latine Book hath a Preface more than I find in the Engliſh, which ſeems to be compiled by the Arch-Biſhop and the reſt of the Reforming Clergy, who give us this reaſon of the tranſlating it into Latine: <hi>Quam Inſtitutionem (Lector Cariſſime) Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtriſſimi ſimul &amp; Religioſiſſimi Principis induſtriâ primum vernaculo ſermone editam, nos nunc in Latinum verſam in lucem damus; Quòd indignum duxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ut hoc pacificandae Eccleſiae ſtudium, &amp; exemplum quo Regia Majeſtas immortalem ſibi gloriam promerita eſt in obſcuro lateret, ac non potius orbi univerſo, quo caeteri Principes ad ſimilem componendae Religionis zelum exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentur innoteſceret: (i. e.)</hi> Which Erudition firſt publiſhed in Engliſh by the Induſtry of our moſt Illuſtrious and Religious Prince, we now publiſh in Latine; as thinking it an unworthy thing, that the care and good Example of pacifying the Church, whereby His Majeſty hath deſerved immortal Glory, ſhould lie hid, and not be known to the World, to ſtir up other Princes to the like Zeal.</p>
            <p>From whence I deſire the Reader to obſerve, that this Book being ſet forth a year after the Engliſh one, and being ſomewhat explained and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, as intended to inform the Foreign Churches with the matter and order of our Reformation, is of the two the more exact and perfect, as containing their ſecond Thoughts and final Reſolutions. The place quoted out of that Book, is that which concerns <hi>The Sacrament of Orders; which</hi> (ſay they) <hi>are given of God to Chriſtian men by the Conſecration and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Biſhops hands.</hi> And doubtleſs King <hi>Henry</hi> would have been very much in wrath with any that ſhould have denied the Order of Biſhops to be Sacramental, when by their hands, and by a <hi>power given them of God,</hi> as is their aſſerted, other Orders were to be conveyed.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, I obſerve, that whereas that Book nameth Biſhops <hi>And</hi> Prieſts as two diſtinct Orders, theſe <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> by a little trick (learnt of the Jeſuits) of changing a ſmall ſyllable, would alter the ſenſe of the whole Chapter: for four or five times in the ſecond and third pages, the <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> name <hi>Biſhops Or Prieſts,</hi> making them one and the ſame thing; which the Reformers in that Chapter of Orders do diſtinguiſh as two diſtinct Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42888:7"/>and eight times at leaſt read <hi>Biſhops And (not Or) Prieſts</hi> in ſenſu diviſo. In the firſt place it is ſaid, that <hi>St.</hi> Paul <hi>did conſecrate and order Prieſts and Biſhops;</hi> for which they quote 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>(i. e.)</hi> Jure Divino. And again, as the <hi>Apoſtles themſelves did order Prieſts and Biſhops,</hi> ſo they <hi>appointed and willed other Biſhops after them to do the like;</hi> for which they quote <hi>Titus</hi> 1. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. which is another Proof out of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. In another place they ſay, that <hi>the Prieſts and Biſhops in the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of their Office and Miniſtration, do uſe and exerciſe the power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of God committed unto them.</hi> And to name but one place more (for I ſhall quote thoſe onely which in the ſenſe of thoſe Reformers (and our Diſſenters too) prove the Order of Biſhops to be diſtinct from that of Prieſts, and of Divine Inſtitution) ſpeaking of the power of the Prince over Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Prieſts, they ſay, that <hi>the Prince is to overſee and cauſe the ſaid Biſhops and Prieſts to execute their Paſtoral Office truly and faithfully, and ſpecially in thoſe points which by Chriſt and his Apoſtles were given and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them.</hi> So that it is undeniable that Biſhops are mentioned as Church-Officers in the New Teſtament by this excellent Book, and conſequently are neceſſary to ſuch a Church-Government as is <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> according to the firſt and ſecond Aſſertion of the Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>Let us inquire therefore how they derive their third Aſſertion from this Book; which is, That <hi>in the New Teſtament there is mention made of no other Church-Officers but Prieſts and Deacons.</hi> (To which words they immediately add) That <hi>no other Government is of Divine Right, but what is under the conduct of Biſhops or Prieſts,</hi> and that <hi>the New Teſtament mentioneth no other:</hi> Which grants that <hi>Biſhops</hi> are mentioned in the New Teſtament as well as <hi>Prieſts.</hi> But the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> will not grant them to be mentioned in the ſenſe of the Reformers (that is) as a diſtinct Office, and having a Superiority over Prieſts and Deacons: for in the</p>
            <p>Fourth Aſſertion they ſay, <hi>That Biſhops or Prieſts, the ſole Governours of the Church, are of one and the ſame Order.</hi> For proof whereof, they quote theſe words out of the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition,</hi> (viz.) <hi>That Biſhops, or Prieſts and Deacons, are the onely Orders mentioned in the New Teſtament</hi>— And that <hi>of theſe two Orders onely,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Prieſts and Deacons, Scripture maketh expreſs mention.</hi> To which I anſwer, That it is no-where ſaid in the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Erudition,</hi> That <hi>Biſhops or Prieſts, the ſole Governours of the Church, are of one and the ſame Order:</hi> And that this Aſſertion is contradicted by the following Quotation upon which they ground it, <hi>(viz.) That Biſhops, or Prieſts and Deacons are the onely Orders mentioned in the New Teſtament.</hi> For throughout that whole Chapter, the Reformers make as plain a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction betwen <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> as between <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Deacons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do therefore reject the firſt Aſſertion as a Fiction of their own, not to be found in the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition,</hi> nor in the practice of the Authors of it, which could beſt expound their meaning, viz. <hi>That Biſhops or Prieſts are of one and the ſame Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:42888:7"/>
            <p>As to the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>of theſe two Orders onely</hi> (i. e.) <hi>of Prieſts and Deacons, the Scripture maketh mention;</hi> I hope to give ſuch a plain and genuine ſenſe of the Authors, as our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> (notwithſtanding all their Prejudices and Evaſions) ſhall not be able to deny. And (becauſe, <hi>Qui benè diſtinguit, benè docet</hi>) I deſire them to obſerve this diſtinction of the word <hi>Order,</hi> which ſignifieth either the Power and Faculty conferred by the Apoſtles hands; or the <hi>Modus,</hi> the Rite and Ceremony of Impoſition of Hands and Prayer, by which it was conferred. The firſt is properly <hi>Order,</hi> and the ſecond, as they term it, <hi>Ordering</hi> or <hi>Ordination.</hi> Now I will not diſpute in which ſenſe our Reformers uſe the word <hi>Order</hi> in this place; the Context will ſhew that: But let the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> take it in which ſenſe they will, it will be ſo far from eſtabliſhing, that it will overthrow their Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, That <hi>Biſhops and Prieſts are one and the ſame Order; and that of theſe two onely Scripture maketh expreſs mention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I grant therefore, that this ſecond ſentence is found intire in that Book, (viz.) <hi>Of theſe two Orders onely,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Prieſts and Deacons, Scripture ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth expreſs mention.</hi> But had theſe men been ſo ingenuous as to quote the whole Paragraph, or to judge of the ſenſe of this Expreſſion, which is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what dark, by thoſe which were more plain, whereof ſome go before, and others follow that ſentence, and all declare Biſhops to be a diſtinct Order, and to be mentioned in the New Teſtament; they would never have had the confidence ſo to expoſe theſe learned Reformers, as if they had contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted themſelves in the ſame breath, and profeſſed their Judgment to be contrary to their Practice, in a Book of that importance, written with great Advice and Deliberation, and publiſhed to give the World an account of the Reformation. Could their Popiſh Adverſaries of that Age have fixed ſuch an Opinion and Contradiction on them, they ſhould have heard of it as loudly as we have of the <hi>Nags head Fable:</hi> but they had not the confidence to feign them guilty of that Opinion which theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> would force on them whether they will or no. For the Papiſts of that Age knew that <hi>Lex currit cum praxi,</hi> and that the Reformers exerciſing Epiſcopal Authority over the Presbyters within their ſeveral Dioceſſes, was a clear proof that they judged their Order to be ſuperiour to that of Prieſts, and that by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution (as in the four places above-mentioned doth appear.)</p>
            <p>But to clear this Objection, I ſhall firſt examine the place quoted as it is entire. Secondly, I ſhall ſhew the ſenſe of it from the Latine Tranſlation, which is the beſt Commentary. And thirdly, from the received Opinion of other Divines of that Age. And fourthly, I ſhall give you Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Opinion of the whole matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> The place quoted ſays thus: <hi>Of theſe two Orders onely</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Prieſts and Deacons, Scripture maketh expreſs mention, and how they were conferred of the Apoſtles by Prayer and Impoſition of their Hands: and to theſe two the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church did add and conjoyn certain</hi> other <hi>inferiour and lower degrees, as Subdeacons, Acolytes, Exorciſts, with divers other, of the which mention is made both of the moſt Ancient Writers that we have in the Church of Chriſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42888:8"/>after the Apoſties; as alſo in divers old Councils, and namely, in the fourth Council of</hi> Africk, <hi>in which St.</hi> Auguſtine <hi>was preſent; where all the kinds of Orders which were then in the Church be rehearſed.</hi> Now though what hath been obſerved from the Context, might be enough to ſatisfie all Perſons that were not maliciouſly diſpoſed to quarrel with thoſe Reformers, as if they contradicted themſelves, and overthrew that Epiſcopal Order <hi>in Theſi,</hi> which they maintained <hi>in Praxi;</hi> yet this Paragraph is ſo clear by its own light, that they muſt needs wink with both eyes that could not ſee the ſenſe of the Reformers in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, the ſcope of the Paragraph ought to have been conſidered, which is to ſpeak of ſuch Orders as were <hi>inferiour to the Apoſtles and Biſhops in Scripture-times;</hi> of which they ſay that <hi>expreſs mention is made in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture onely of theſe two,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Prieſts and Deacons:</hi> To which two, though the Church added <hi>other inferiour and lower degrees</hi> mentioned in Ancient Writers (yet there is no mention of them in the Scripture, but) in ſome old Councils, and namely, in the four <hi>African,</hi> where all the kinds of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders be rehearſed. Now in that Council you may find the ſeveral Rites of Ordaining. 1. Biſhops, 2. Presbyters, 3. Deacons, 4. Subdeacons, 5. Aco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lythi, 6. Exorciſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And Canon 27. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Epiſcopus de loco ignobile ad no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem non tranſeat, nec quiſquam inferioris ordinis Clericus: Inferioris vero gradus Sacerdotes poſſunt conceſſione ſuorum Epiſcoporum ad alias Eccleſias mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grare.</hi> So that in the Judgment of that Council, Prieſts were an inferiour Order to Biſhops; and conſequently they were ſo in the Judgment of our Reformers, who quote it to that end. See <hi>Binius,</hi> Tom. 1. p. 728.</p>
            <p>This alſo appears from the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Council, which is alſo quoted by the Reformers, in which St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was alſo preſent; wherein a Canon was made, <hi>Quo prohibiter ne Presbyteri, Diaconi, vel caeteri</hi> inferiores Clerici <hi>in cauſis ſuis ulla extra Africam adeant judicia.</hi> So that by both theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, <hi>Prieſts</hi> as well as <hi>Deacons</hi> are proved to be <hi>inferiour</hi> to <hi>Biſhops:</hi> which was the thing intended by our Reformers in that Paragraph.</p>
            <p>So that when theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> (from this paſſage, <hi>(viz,)</hi> that of <hi>theſe two Orders onely,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Prieſts and Deacons, Scripture maketh expreſs men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>) do in the words immediately following infer, That <hi>all others</hi> (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing particularly that of <hi>Biſhops</hi>) were afterward added by the Church, <hi>p.</hi> 2. and name this inference as if it were the very words of that excellent Book, is no leſs a ſin, than the bearing falſe witneſs againſt them; for they treat onely of other inferiour and lower degrees. So that if the word <hi>Order</hi> be taken in the firſt ſenſe, for the power or faculty of adminiſtring holy things conferred by the Biſhops, it is their plain ſenſe, That <hi>the Scripture maketh expreſs mention of theſe two inferiour Orders onely,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Priests and Deacons,</hi> and not of Subdeacons, Acolytes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, two things eſpecially ſeem deſigned by the Reformers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Sacrament of Orders:</hi> The firſt is to ſhew that Biſhops are of Divine Inſtitution, and had not their dependance on the Pope, whom his Favourites made the only Biſhop, and all the reſt deriving their power and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42888:8"/>authority from him. The ſecond was to ſhew, that of all thoſe <hi>ſeven Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> which were made <hi>Sacramental,</hi> onely thoſe of <hi>Biſhops, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> had foundation in Scripture; the reſt were added in after-times. And to confirm both theſe, they deſcribe the manner of ordaining both Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons in the Holy Scripture, to diſcharge it from thoſe ſuperſtitious Ceremonies introduced by the Pope, and made neceſſary to their Ordination. As for the <hi>Superiority</hi> of Biſhops to Prieſts, there is no queſtion made, much leſs of their <hi>Identity</hi> or <hi>ſameneſs</hi> of Office.</p>
            <p>For the Divine Right of Biſhops, they aſſert it in four ſeveral places, that they have it from Chriſt; and prove it by Scripture, and from thence infer this Concluſion, That whereas the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath heretofore claimed and uſurped to be Head and Governour of all Biſhops and Prieſts of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, by the Laws of God; it is evident that his Power is utterly feigned and untrue, and was neither given him by God in Holy Scripture, nor allowed by the Fathers in Ancient General Councils, nor by conſent of the Cotholick Church. And they declare, That the Authorities, Powers, and Juriſdictions of Patriarchs, Primates, Arch-biſhops; and Metropolitans, were given them by the poſitive Laws of men onely, and not by any Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God in Holy Scripture. And the power uſurped by any one Biſhop over another, (not given him by the Conſent of men) is no lawful Power, but plain Uſurpation and Tyranny: Which they prove from the Ancient Councils and Fathers againſt the Pope. Secondly, They ſhew, that of thoſe <hi>ſeven Orders</hi> owned by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as <hi>Sacramental,</hi> onely Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, had their Inſtitution in the Holy Scripture; and that Subdeacons, Acolytes, Exorciſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were added by the Church, as alſo the Rites and Ceremonies by which they were conferred. And third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to confirm what they had ſaid, they deſcribe the manner of ordaining Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, to clear it from thoſe ſuperſtitious Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies brought in by the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> as the Ring and Croſier-ſtaff, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Unctions and Garments, ſome of which muſt come from <hi>Rome;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Scripture mentions onely the impoſition of Hands and Prayers. In theſe words, <hi>Of theſe two Orders onely,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Prieſts and Deacons, the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture maketh expreſs mention;</hi> and how <hi>they were conferred of the Apoſtles by Prayer and impoſition of their Hands.</hi> And evident it is to me, that by the word <hi>Orders</hi> they intended onely the manner of Ordaining, not the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Orders: for they all held the Superiority of Biſhops to Prieſts. And this will appear, firſt, from the word uſed by the Latine Tranſlation, which is, <hi>De his tantum Ordinationibus,</hi> of theſe Ordinations onely, not of theſe two Orders onely, the Scripture makes mention, and deſcribeth the manner of conferring them. And doubtleſs thoſe learned men did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the words <hi>Ordo</hi> and <hi>Ordinatio.</hi> For the underſtanding whereof, I ſhall explain the Engliſh Edition by the Latine.</p>
            <p>Thus in the beginning they ſay, That <hi>theſe Orders were given by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration and Impoſition of the Biſhops hands: [Per Conſecrationem &amp; Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitionem manum Epiſcopi.]</hi> And as the Apoſtles themſelves in the beginning
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42888:9"/>of the Church did order Prieſts and Biſhops; ſo they willed the other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to the like. Thus the Latine Book: <hi>Et</hi> Quemadmodum <hi>Apoſtoli ipſi Epiſcopos &amp; Presbyteros</hi> Ordinaverunt, ita, <hi>eoſdem etiam inſtituiſſe ut in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterum ſuccedentes Epiſcopi</hi> eundem ordinandi morem <hi>in Eccleſia ſervarent.</hi> Again, <hi>Here is to be noted, That although this Form before declared is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in giving Orders,</hi> &amp;c. in the Latine, <hi>Quanquam autem</hi> hunc in modum <hi>Scriptura Ordinationes fieri inſtituit.</hi> Again, <hi>Thus we have briefly touched the Ordering, not the Orders of Priests and Biſhops.</hi> The Latine, <hi>Hactonus quidem</hi> de Ordinatione <hi>Presbyterorum.</hi> Neither ſpeak of the <hi>Order,</hi> but <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering.</hi> Moreover, touching the Order of Deacons, we read <hi>Acts</hi> 6. that they were ordered and inſtituted by the ſame Apoſtles by Prayer and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of their hands. The Latine, <hi>Jam vero praeter</hi> Epiſcopos &amp; Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes, Diaconorum etiam Scriptura meminit, <hi>traditque hos ab Apostolis per Orationem &amp; manuum impoſitionem ordinatos &amp; institutos fuiſſe.</hi> After all which it followeth, <hi>Of theſe two Orders onely,</hi> (which I cannot underſtand (the premiſes being conſidered) in any other ſenſe than as the Latine ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it) Of theſe <hi>Ordinations</hi> onely, and how they were conferred, the Scripture maketh mention, That they were conferred by Prayer and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands. Nor can it be thought that by the mentioning the <hi>manner of ordaining</hi> Biſhops and Prieſts to be the ſame, that therefore the Reformers thought the <hi>Order</hi> to be the ſame; becauſe the Deacons were ordained in the ſame manner, and yet it is granted that they were diſtinct Orders And for the diſtinction of the Orders of Prieſts and Biſhops, enough had been ſpoken before, and their preſent practice did demonſtrate what their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions were.</p>
            <p>If any deſire farther ſatisfaction in theſe things, let him read the Caſuiſts <hi>de Sacramento Ordinis,</hi> where this diſtinction is obvious: <hi>Ordo ſignificat vel ipſam potestatem, vel Ordinationem quâ potestas datur.</hi> And they may find that <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and generally the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> reckon Biſhops and Prieſts to be but one Order, as our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> would have it: and among the later School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men it was made a Queſtion, <hi>An Epiſcopatus ſit Ordo à Presbyteratu distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus;</hi> and they generally hold that they are one in <hi>Genere Sacerdotis,</hi> but are diſtinct in <hi>Specie,</hi> the Epiſcopal Character including that of a Prieſt; and ſo they hold that <hi>Solum Sacerdotium est Ordo &amp; Sacramentum.</hi> So they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute againſt the Impoſition of hands in Ordination of Prieſts; and the uſual form was by delivering the Patine and Chalice, with Bread and Wine, with theſe words: <hi>Accipe potestatem offerendi Sacrificia pro vivis &amp; mortuis, In nomine Patris, &amp;c.</hi> And they affirm, That the Pope can create a Biſhop or Prieſt, onely by ſaying, <hi>Be thou a Biſhop or Priest</hi>— A Deacon is ordained by delivering of the Goſpels into his hands, and the Subdeacon by delivery of an empty Patine and Chalice: Which ſuperſtitious uſes our Reformers would deſtroy, and reduce to the Apoſtolical Practice.</p>
            <p>One Argument more theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> mention from the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition,</hi> as good as the reſt, p. 3. <hi>The Order of a Biſhop or Priest is one and the ſame, whoſe Office is not onely to preach and administer Sacraments, but moreover to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42888:9"/>exerciſe Diſcipline, namely, in aſſoyling and looſing from ſin ſuch as be truly penitent, and in excommunicating the obſtinately vicious;</hi> where from the Community of ſome Offices, they would argue to the equality of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: though nothing is more evident, than that the Biſhops of this Age re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the power of <hi>Confirmation, Ordination,</hi> and <hi>Dioceſan Juriſdiction</hi> to themſelves, as their Right <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> as will yet further appear. But no-where doth the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition</hi> ſay, That the Order of a Biſhop or Prieſt is one and the ſame, as they ſophiſtically infer: And they may as well affirm it to be the ſence of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> as of our Reformers, who uſe almoſt the ſame words, <hi>Non ſolum Sacerdotibus, ſed &amp; de Diaconis, Sacrae Literae apertam mentionem faciunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot conceive what ground theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> had to fix this Errour of theirs upon, unleſs an unwary Expreſſion of Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s; who perhaps con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Arch-biſhop's Judgment, more than the Judgments of the reſt, doth aſſert the ſame as the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> do: But if they had it from him, they had alſo in him a correction of this Error; and it was far from the ingenuity of true Proteſtant Divines, to publiſh the Error, and conceal the Confutation of it. Thus then Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> diſcovers the whole Intrigue, Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> p. 336. of the firſt part, <hi>That both in this Writing</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Manuſcript) and in the <hi>Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Erudition of a Chriſtian man, Biſhops and Prieſts are ſpoken of as one and the ſame Office.</hi> But Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> adds, <hi>In the ancient Church they knew none of thoſe ſubtilties which were found out in the later Ages; it was then thought enough that a Biſhop was to be dedicated to his Function by a new Impoſition of hands, and that ſeveral Offices could not be performed without a Biſhop, ſuch as Ordination, Confirmation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But they did not refine in theſe matters ſo much as to enquire whether Biſhops and Prieſts differed in Order and Office, or only in degree: But after the School-men fell to examine matters of Dignity with logical and unintelligible Niceties, the Canoniſts began to comment upon the Rules of the Ancient Church, they ſtudied to make Biſhops and Prieſts ſeem very near one to another, ſo that the difference was but ſmall. They did it with different deſigns: The School-men having ſet up the grand Myſtery of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, were to exalt the Prieſtly Office as much as was poſſible; for the turning of the Host into God, was ſo great an action, that they reckoned there could be no Office higher than that which qualified a man to ſo mighty a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance. Therefore as they changed the form of Ordination from what it was anciently believed to conſist in,</hi> (viz.) <hi>Impoſition of hands, to a delivering of Sacred Veſſels; and held that a Priest had his Orders by that Rite, not by the Impoſition of hands: So they raiſed their Order or Office ſo high, as to make it equal with the Order of a Biſhop. But as they deſigned to extol the Order of Prieſthood, ſo the Canoniſts had as great a mind to depreſs the Epiſcopal Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; they generally wrote for preferment, and the way to it, was to extol the Papacy: Nothing could do that ſo effectually, as to bring down the power of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; this only could juſtifie the Exemptions of the Monks and Friars, the Popes ſetting up Legantine Courts, and receiving at firſt Appeals, and then Original Cauſes before them, together with many other Encroachments on the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42888:10"/>Juriſdiction of Biſhops; all which were unlawful, if the Biſhops had by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right Juriſdiction in their Dioceſſes: Therefore it was neceſſary to lay them as low as could be, and to make them think that the power they held was rather as delegates of the Apoſtolick See, than by a Commiſſion from Christ or his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties. So that they looked on the declaring Epiſcopal Authority to be of Divine Right, as a blow that would be fatal to the Court of</hi> Rome; <hi>therefore they did after this at</hi> Trent, <hi>uſe all poſſible endeavours to hinder any ſuch Deciſion: it having been then the common Stile of that Age, to reckon Biſhops and Prieſts as the ſame Office, it is no wonder if at this time the Clergy of this Church, the greatest part of them being ſtill leavened with the old Superſtition, and the rest of them not having enough of ſpare time to examine leſſer matters, retain ſtill the former Phraſes in this particular.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This might have been ſufficient to correct the forwardneſs of our <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> to comply with the Papiſts in this new Notion of Biſhops or Prieſts as one Order; but becauſe they abated nothing of their confidence by this, I ſhall mind them of that ſeverer Reprimand of the Doctor's, for which in their behalf I give him hearty thanks, for I think he ſhall have none from them. It is in theſe words (N. B.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>On this I have inſiſted the more, that it may appear how little they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered things, who are ſo far carried with their Zeal against the eſtabliſhed Government of this Church, as to make much uſe of ſome paſſages of the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Canoniſts that deny them to be diſtinct Orders: for theſe are the very dregs of Popery (N. B.) the one raiſing the Prieſts higher for the ſake of</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, <hi>the other pulling the Biſhops lower for the ſake of the</hi> Popes Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, <hi>and by ſuch means bringing them almost to an equality. So partial are ſome men to their particular Conceits, that they make uſe of the most miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Topicks when they can ſerve their turn, not conſidering how much far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe Arguments will run if they ever admit them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that although the Phraſe of <hi>Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Biſhops.</hi> might have been uſed in former times, as it was in a Paper printed among the <hi>Addenda</hi> to the firſt part of the Doctor's Hiſtory, <hi>p.</hi> 324. which Paper was written about ſix years before the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition,</hi> as is proved, <hi>p.</hi> 365. of the firſt part: Yet when our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> read (as no doubt they did) theſe Remarks of the Doctor's concerning the riſe and miſchievous tendences of it, their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in urging it from that Paper where it is ſo ſhamefully condemned, is as unpardonable as their endeavour to faſten it on the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition,</hi> where the contrary is evidently aſſerted.</p>
            <p>And is this the great Reverence that our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have for the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, thus to wreſt and abuſe their Writings, by altering their Words, curtailing their Sentences, and repreſenting them as contradicting themſelves, as well as the Univerſal Church in all Ages before them, in ſuch an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Book, and to object that againſt them, which their Adverſaries, who watched for ſuch an advantage, could never find? This is no otherwiſe to honour them, than to call them to a ſecond Martyrdom, more inglorious and hateful to them than the firſt. And yet theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> could not but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42888:10"/>know, that all they who had a hand in compiling that Book, were either Dioceſan Biſhops, or ſuch Divines as lived in a willing ſubmiſſion to them. And theſe things are ſufficient to ſhew that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are more genuine Sons of ſome other Church, than of the Church of <hi>England</hi> according to its Primitive Conſtitution.</p>
            <p>And thus the Declaration mentioned by our Author to be ſubſcribed by <hi>Tho. Cromwell,</hi> &amp;c. which ſays, <hi>That in the New Teſtament there is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of any degrees or diſtinctions in Orders, but only of Deacons or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Prieſts or Biſhops;</hi> as alſo the Opinions of <hi>Tindal, Lambert,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Barnes,</hi> muſt be ſubmitted to the more mature and authorized Judgment of the State, Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, expreſſed in the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition.</hi> And the private Sentiments of ſuch Divines as have written from the days of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> VI. until now, muſt be adjudged to be conformable to the Judgment and Determination of the Church, which hath been eſtabliſhed by Law in their days, to which alſo they generally ſubſcribed; and then I need ſay no more, but that the Forms of Ordaining and Conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, will determine the Queſtion; whether from the beginning of our Reformation, the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath acknowledged three Orders, <hi>viz.</hi> of Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, or two only; And whether the Church-Government eſtabliſhed by Law ever ſince the days of <hi>Edward</hi> VI. hath not been by Dioceſan Biſhops.</p>
            <p>But I would ask theſe men, Could they have conformed to <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> and <hi>Liturgy</hi> under King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, or <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, and can they not now? Was not <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> the ſame then as it is now; and the <hi>Liturgie</hi> much better now than it was then? Could you conform to <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's <hi>Primer,</hi> to his <hi>ſix Articles</hi> and <hi>ſeven Sacraments?</hi> Or to the <hi>Liturgie</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, wherein were many things that were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly accounted <hi>Ineptias?</hi> As in the <hi>Communion-Office,</hi> where they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to the mercy of God <hi>all his Servants departed hence from us;</hi> And that God would <hi>command our Prayers and Supplications by the miniſtry of his holy Angels to be brought up into his holy Tabernacle:</hi> The commending <hi>Auricular</hi> and <hi>Secret Confeſſion</hi> to the Prieſt: And in the Office of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> enjoyning a great part of that Office to be performed <hi>the people ſtanding at the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door;</hi> and then to <hi>take the Child by the right hand, and lead it towards the Font:</hi> To <hi>ſign it with the ſign of the Croſs on the Breast,</hi> as well as the <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</hi> The uſe of <hi>Exorciſm,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>I command thee, thou unclean Spirit, in the Name of the Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to come out and depart from this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant. The dipping the Child three times in the Water, (except in caſe of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) first on the right ſide, then on the left, and then with the Face towards the Water.</hi> Then to put on it the <hi>Cryſom,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Take thou this white Veſture for a Token of the Innocency,</hi> &amp;c. Then to <hi>anoint the Infant on the head, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God to anoint him with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction of the Spirit.</hi> And (to omit many other things) <hi>anointing the ſick, and ſigning his breast with the ſign of the Croſs.</hi> Commending at the time of Burial <hi>into the hands of God's mercy the Souls of the departed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:42888:11"/>
            <p>As for the Book of <hi>conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons,</hi> it was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the <hi>Liturgie</hi> by King <hi>Edward,</hi> as it is received now, with ſome few alterations (mentioned by Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>) for the better, <hi>p.</hi> 144.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Articles,</hi> and <hi>Acts for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> were as ſevere as any that are now. And all theſe were eſtabliſhed in Arch-biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi>'s time, and with his good Approbation.</p>
            <p>In the Articles of Religion, printed 1552. one concerning the Liturgy declares thus. <hi>The Book</hi> (of Prayers) <hi>which of very late time was given to the Church of</hi> England <hi>by the Authority of Parliament, containing the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Form of praying, and miniſtring the Sacraments; and the Book of ordering Miniſters of the Church, ſet forth by the afore ſaid Authority, are godly, and in no point repugnant to the wholſome Doctrine of the Goſpel, but agreeing thereunto, furthering and beautifying the ſame not a little; and therefore of all faithful Miniſters of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and chiefly of the Miniſters of the Lord, ought to be received and allowed with all readineſs of mind and thanksgiving, and to be commended to the people of God.</hi> Beſides the Diſcourſe <hi>concerning Ceremonies retained</hi> in our Book, was then ſet forth; as alſo a <hi>Proclamation</hi> againſt thoſe that <hi>innovate, alter, or leave down any Rite or Ceremony in the Church, and that preach without Licenſe;</hi> printed in the ſecond year of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, (to which the Form for <hi>Bidding of Prayers</hi> may be added.) See <hi>p.</hi> 128. of Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s ſecond part. All which notwithſtanding, <hi>Bucer</hi> and <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> approved of Conformity.</p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf both perſwaded and approved all that was done in the ſecond Liturgy of King <hi>Edward,</hi> in an Epiſtle of his to the then <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector,</hi> being the forty firſt Epiſtle in the Edition at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> 1667. to this effect: <q>Let there be publiſhed a Summary of Doctrine to be received by all, which all may conform to in their preaching; for the obſervance of which, let all Biſhops and Pariſh-Prieſts be obliged by Oath; and let none be admitted to Eccleſiaſtical Function, unleſs he promiſe to obſerve that conſent of Doctrine inviolate. Let there be alſo a common form of Catechiſm for the uſe of Children: I alſo greatly approve that there be a certain Form of Prayers and Eccleſiaſtical Rites, from which it ſhould not be lawful for the Paſtors to recede in their Function; as well to provide for the ſimplicity and unskilfulneſs of ſome, as alſo that thereby the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all the Churches may more certainly appear; and laſtly, that the deſultory levity of ſome men, who affect Novelties, may be prevented. So that there ought to be an eſtabliſhed Catechiſm, an eſtabliſhed Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments, and publick Form of Prayers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Did not Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> a learned Martyr, declare of the Liturgy as it ſtood in <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's days, that according to the Rules of our Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in every behalf, <hi>no Chriſtian Conſcience could be offended with any thing therein contained?</hi> And is it well done to fill the Conſciences of the People now with Scruples againſt almoſt every part of it? How theſe men would have demeaned themſelves under the Impoſitions and Biſhops in the days of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, and <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, I cannot divine, Uniformity being
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42888:11"/>as ſtrictly enjoyned then, as it is now. For ſuch as did <hi>officiate in any other manner than was preſcribed by the Liturgie, were for the first Offence to ſuffer ſix months Impriſonment; for the ſecond, to be impriſoned during life: and if any ſhould print in defamation of it, or threaten Clergy men for uſing of it, he was to be fined</hi> 10 <hi>l. for the first Offence,</hi> 20 <hi>l. for the ſecond, and for the third to forfeit all his Goods, and ſuffer Impriſonment during life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for the Reign of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> let the <hi>Book of Martyrs</hi> be viewed, and it will appear that they who bore Teſtimony to the Truths of Chriſt, and truly deſerved the name of <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> were ſuch as were eminent Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertors of the <hi>eſtabliſhed Epiſcopacy</hi> and <hi>Liturgie;</hi> ſuch as <hi>Cranmer, Ridley, Latimer, Hooper, Taylor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Leſt I ſhould lead my Reader into an Error, while I follow the Method of theſe Men, I thought fit to inform the Reader, That the <hi>Erudition of a Chriſtian Man</hi> was printed in the Year 1543. and the Reſolution of the Queſtions mentioned in the Papeer by Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> in the days of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth; which whether they were conſulted of before <hi>(viz.)</hi> in the days of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, is not material to enquire into: but the Method Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> uſed in the Reply to the Defence of Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> in the Preface, ſaying, in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's time, <hi>Cranmer,</hi> in Anſwer to that Queſtion, <hi>Whether Biſhops or Prieſts were firſt?</hi> did aſſert, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that he did not vary from that Opinion, the ſame being by him aſſerted in the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Erudition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Opinion of thoſe three Divines which are mentioned in this Chapter, <hi>viz. Tindal, Lambert,</hi> and <hi>Barnes,</hi> the firſt ſays, <hi>That the Apoſtles ordained two Officers</hi> (viz.) <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Overſeer,</hi> and <hi>Deacon</hi> or <hi>Miniſter;</hi> and adds, <hi>That Deacons crept not into Orders till the Church grew Rich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lambert</hi> he ſays was of the ſame Opinion, which he took from St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> who held Biſhops and Prieſts to be one and the ſame (of which we ſhall ſpeak hereafter). This <hi>Lambert</hi> was a ſtranger, come from <hi>Avignon,</hi> and would that every Pariſh ſhould have his proper Biſhop, and in every City there ought to be many Biſhops: This Mr. <hi>Barnes</hi> denies, and quotes St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>I have left thee behind me to ſet in every City a Biſhop.</hi> And the Article againſt Mr. <hi>Barnes</hi> was, That he held, that one Man might not by the Law of God be a Biſhop of Two or Three Cities, or of a whole Country; he denyed not one Biſhop in a City, but thought that an Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Inſtitution: His Opinion was, <hi>That there ought not to be ſuch Biſhops as the Cardinal that examined him was:</hi> Who told Mr. <hi>Barnes, That this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle toucht him.</hi> And it ſeems evident, that this Man ſpake againſt ſuch U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpations as the Pope and Cardinals exerciſed; wherein he agreed to the Sentiments of all thoſe that ſubſcribed the neceſſary <hi>Erudition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now there remains little too be ſaid of <hi>Ch.</hi> 2. for that which he ſays from a Statute <hi>primo Edw.</hi> 6. was brought in by a Parentheſis, as not part of the intention of the Statute, which was to be learnt from the Preamble, <hi>(viz.) That the Election of Biſhops ſhould not be in the Deans and Chapters, to prevent Delays and Expences, but in the King:</hi> So that it reſpects only the External
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42888:12"/>Government of the Church, which is ſtill acknowledged to be in the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Magiſtrate, who is Supreme in all Cauſes, and over all Perſons. And therefore it needed not that Reflection of Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> which our Author mentioneth, <hi>viz. That it did weaken the Authority of the Epiſcopal Order:</hi> Which, (as hath been proved from the <hi>Erudition,</hi> and the Judgment of the Divines mentioned in Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Paper) was from Chriſt.</p>
            <p>As to Biſhop <hi>Poynet,</hi> the ſum of what he ſays is this, <hi>Who knows not that the Name Biſhop hath been ſo abuſed, that when it was ſpoken the People un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood no other thing but a great Lord,</hi> — (Where he ſeems to deſcribe a Cardinal, or Popiſh Biſhop) <hi>that went in a white Rochet, with a wide ſhaven Crown, and that carried an Oil-Box with him, wherewith he uſeth once in Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Years, Riding about, to Confirm Children.</hi> Certainly, he could not mean this of Dioceſan Proteſtant Biſhops, he being then Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter;</hi> and the Name of Biſhop being thus abuſed, he thought it not amiſs, if another word were uſed in its place, till the abuſed word were reſtored to its right Signification; and then adds: <hi>O how the Papiſts would triumph over us, if they had like proof for the Names of Pope, Cardinal,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as we have for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Names Superintendent,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>in his ſenſe, Biſhop, Miniſter, and ſuch-like by us uſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ch.</hi> 3. He ſays, That <hi>Aley</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter, Pilkington</hi> of <hi>Durham, Jewel</hi> of <hi>Salisbury, Whitgift</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> were of the ſame Opinion with <hi>Tindal, Lambert,</hi> and <hi>Barnes,</hi> and the Reformers in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s time, and what that was hath been conſidered; I only obſerve in general, that all theſe were Dioceſan Biſhops, and therefore probably would write nothing to deſtroy their own Order, That which Biſhop <hi>Aley</hi> ſays, is a Quotation from St. <hi>Hierome, That a Presbyter and Biſhop are the ſame,</hi> &amp;c. But, ſaith Biſhop <hi>Aley,</hi> it grew by little and little, that the whole charge and care ſhould be appointed to one Biſhop within his Precinct. Our Author mentions another Quotation from the Biſhop out of St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> viz. <hi>That Biſhops are greater than Prieſts, rather by Cuſtome than by Diſpenſation from the Lord;</hi> of which hereafter. To the ſame effect he quotes <hi>Pilkington</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> arguing againſt a Popiſh Author, and therefore probably againſt Popiſh Biſhops; and he ſays, <hi>That God's Commiſſion is alike to all, Prieſt, Biſhop, Archbiſhop, and Prelate;</hi> for which he quotes St. <hi>Hierome, ad Evagrium, That a Biſhop where-ever he be, is of the ſame Power and Prieſthood,</hi> which he urged againſt thoſe that ſtill claimed their Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> uſurped Power above Princes, and other Biſhops; who as this Biſhop ſays, had no Authority to Suſpend, Deprive, and Interdict any Prieſt that paid not his Subſidies, but from the Parliament: I cannot ſee what inference the Author can make from this to favour his Opinion.</p>
            <p>The ſum of what Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> ſays, is that of St. <hi>Hierome, That all Prieſts are of the ſame Power; that the Names of Metropolitans, Archbiſhops, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are not found in the SS.</hi> That St. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſays, <hi>Sciant Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi;</hi> that they are in Authority over Prieſts more by Cuſtome, than by Order of God's Truth: And againſt <hi>Harding</hi> he ſays, <hi>What meant Mr.</hi> Harding <hi>to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42888:12"/>come in with the difference between Prieſts and Biſhops, thinketh he that Prieſts and Biſhops hold only by Tradition; or is it ſo humble a Hereſie to ſay, that by the SS of God, a Biſhop and a Priest are all one:</hi> He grants alſo, <hi>That it is by the favour of Princes, that a Priest being found negligent,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he may be puniſhed by the diſcretion of the Biſhop. That the Matters of Government must be taken out of the Word of God:</hi> (viz) <hi>That the Word be truly taught, the Sacraments rightly adminiſtred, Vertue furthered, Vice repreſſed, and the Church kept in Quietneſs and Order: That the Officers whereby this Government is wrought, be not namely and particularly expreſſed in SS. but left to the diſcretion of the Church, according to the ſtate of Times, Places, and Perſons; and therefore no certain and perfect kind of Government being preſcribed in SS, as neceſſary to the Salvation of the Church, the ſame may be altered:</hi> For which he quotes <hi>Gualter— Let every Church follow the manner of Diſcipline which doth most agree with the people, and most fit for the time and place; and let no Man raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſcribe to others, and bind all Churches to one Form: It is well known, that the Manner and Form of Government in the Apoſtles times, and expreſſed in the SS, neither is now, nor can, nor ought to be obſerved.</hi> This he wrote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Cartwright,</hi> pleading for his Government, as if preſcribed in SS, and thus he applies it to the then Diſſenters: <hi>If you will have the Queen Rule as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch in her own Dominions, you must give her leave to uſe one kind and form of Government, in all, and every part, and ſo to Govern the Church in Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Affairs, as in Civil.</hi> I wiſh they would follow his Example and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that ſo ſeem to recommend his Judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ch.</hi> 4. begins with Dr. <hi>Willet</hi>'s Opinion, who ſays, <q>That of the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between Biſhops and Prieſts there are Three Opinions; the firſt of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> who held that all Miniſters ſhould be equal; and that a Biſhop was not, nor ought to be ſuperiour to a Prieſt; nor was there any difference at all between them.</q> Which Opinion was counted an Hereſie. <hi>N. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second in the other extream is of the Papiſts, <q>That would have not only a difference, but a Princely Preheminence of their Biſhops over the Clergy, and that by the Word of God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Third Opinion between both, is: <q>That although this diſtinction of Biſhops and Prieſts, as now received, cannot be directly proved out of SS, yet it is very good for the Polity of the Church, to avoid Schiſm and to preſerve it in Unity: And he concludes.</q> So then here is a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween our Adverſaries the Papiſts, and us; they ſay, It is of neceſſity to Salvation to be ſubject to the Pope, and to Biſhops, and Archbiſhops under him, as neceſſarily preſcribed in the Word: But ſo do not our Biſhops and Archbiſhops, which is a notable difference between the Biſhops of the Popiſh Church, and the Reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>Let every Church uſe the Form which beſt fitteth their State in External Matters. <hi>N. B.</hi> Every Church is free, not one bound to the Preſcription of another: So they meaſure themſelves by the Rule of the Word. This then (he ſays) may without any contradiction be affirmed, that in this diſtinction of the Miniſters of the Church, there is ſomewhat Apoſtolical, ſomewhat alſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42888:13"/>Political: Firſt, in the calling of Biſhops, as now ordained in ſome Reformed Church, it cannot be denied but that we have Order in the Church; and to have diverſity of Degrees and Miniſtrations, to avoid Confuſion, proceeds from an Inſtitution of Chriſt, that there ſhould not be a popular Equality, but a convenient Superiority, and Priority in the Miniſters of the Goſpel; as St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſheweth: Firſt Apoſtles, ſecond Prophets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Secondly, There is ſomewhat Politick, and that of two ſorts, as touching the Polity Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical and Civil. To the Eccleſiaſtical, in advancing the Dignity of Biſhops theſe things appertain: 1. St. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſays of Confirmation, That it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted only to Biſhops; that it is rather for the honour of the Prieſthood, then by neceſſity of any Law. 2. The Council of <hi>Aquiſgrane,</hi> ch. 8, ſaith, <q>That the Ordination and Conſecration of Miniſters is now reſerved to the chief Miniſter only for Authority's-ſake, leſt that the Diſcipline of the Church being changed by many, ſhould break the Peace of the Church.</q> 3. The Author of the Book under <hi>Hierome</hi>'s Name, <hi>De Septem Ordinibus,</hi> ſaith, <q>That the Conſecration of Virgins, which is not now in uſe in the Reformed Churches, was reſerved to the Biſhop for Concord's ſake.</q> 4. The Juriſdiction of the Church, which in times paſt (<hi>Hierome</hi> ſays) was committed to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Presbyters, was afterwards, to avoid Schiſm, devolved to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. Among other Inferences from Dr. <hi>Willet,</hi> he concludes, <q>That <hi>Willet</hi> indeed ſaith, that for the ſake of Order, the Preſidence of one above the reſt is Divine and Apoſtolical: And at the latter end of Queen <hi>Eligabeth,</hi>
               </q> the Epiſcopal Government is affirm'd to be Apoſtolical, and a Divine Inſtitution. And as to <hi>Saravia,</hi> our Author gives his Judgment in theſe two particulars, differing from <hi>Whitgift:</hi> 1. That not only the Miniſtry of the Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, but the Form of Government inſtituted by the Lord himſelf, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the Apoſtles, confirmed by the Fathers, ought to be continued for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. 2. The Superiority in degree of a Biſhop, above a Presbyter, is a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution; and that St. <hi>Hierome</hi> was in the ſame Error with <hi>Arrius: Dico privatam fuiſſe Hieronimi Opinionem conſentaneam cum Arrio &amp; Dei ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo contrariam.</hi> The laſt that he mentioneth in this <hi>Ch.</hi> is Biſhop <hi>Bancroft,</hi> who ſays, <q>We have a Church-Government, which in my Conſcience is truly Apoſtolical, and far to be preferred before any other received this day in any Reformed Church in <hi>Chriſtendome.</hi>
               </q> And after the Death of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who did overſee both Churches, Paſtors, and Biſhops, or Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtories, and ancient Fathers have kept a Regiſter of their Names, who Succeeded and Ruled the Churches after them.—And this inequality hath been approved and honoured by all the Ancient Fathers, none excepted, and by all the General Councils, and by all other Men of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for many hundred Years after the Apoſtles time, ſaving <hi>Arrius</hi> the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, who miſſing of a Biſhoprick that he ſhed for, firſt broached the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, That there ought to be no difference between a Biſhop and a Prieſt. <hi>N. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which Biſhop <hi>Bancroft</hi> notes from Dr. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> is this: <q>I have maintain'd that the Titles of Honour given to our Biſhops, are no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42888:13"/>to the Word, than for us to be called Wardens or Preſidents of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and in my Judgment they may with as good Conſcience be Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of their Dioceſs, as we being Miniſters may Govern Colledges of Mr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. Nor do I think this was a late deviſed Polity; for I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the Angel of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> to whom St. <hi>John</hi> writes, was one Miniſter ſet over the reſt; for why, ſeeing there were many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors there, ſhould St. <hi>John</hi> write to the Angel, and not to the Angels, if there had been no difference among them; neither if this Preſidency had had that fault which is reproved in <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> would our Saviour, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth thoſe Diſorders which he found in the Seven Churches, have paſſed over this great fault in ſilence; therefore as <hi>Titus</hi> was left in <hi>Greet</hi> to reform the Churches in that whole Iſland, ſo I am perſwaded, that in other Places ſome of that Order, and of Paſtors and Teachers, which is perpetual in the Church, even in the time of the Apoſtles, and had a Prelacy among their Brethren, and that this Preheminence is approved by our Saviour. And to come lower, tho' the word <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> ſignifieth, that care which is required of all, and be in SS required of all that have care of Souls; yet I do not remember any one Eccleſiaſtical Writer wherein that word doth not import a greater Dignity than is common to all Miniſters; neither do I think that any old Writer did under the Name of Biſhop mean the Paſtor of every Pariſh: Thus Dr. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> with whom, if Dr. <hi>Raynolds</hi> do agree, I ſee not <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> whether the Factioners will turn them; for this Doctor in his Book againſt <hi>Hart</hi> ſaith, That in the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> though it had ſundry Elders and Paſtors to guide it, yet among thoſe was there one Chief, whom our Saviour calleth the Angel of the Church; and this is he, whom after, in the Primitive Church, the Fathers called Biſhop: For, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> He proceeds thus:</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Name of Biſhop, common before to all Elders and Paſtors of the Church, was then, by the uſual Language of the Fathers, appropriated to him who had the Preſidentſhip over the Elders. Thus are certain Elders reproved by St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> for receiving to the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them who had fallen in time of Perſecution, before the Biſhop had advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with them, and others.</q> Theſe Two are for <hi>Oxford,</hi> touching the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Ancient Fathers, ſpeaking of Biſhops. Now you ſhall have a <hi>Cambridge</hi> Man's Opinion, Dr. <hi>Fulke,</hi> who in confutation of the <hi>Rbemiſh</hi> Teſtament, ſays: <q>Among the Clergy for Order and ſeemly Government, there was always one Principal, to whom, by long uſe of the Church, the Name of Biſhop, or Superintendant hath been applied; which room <hi>Titus</hi> exerciſed in <hi>Creet, Timothy</hi> in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and others in other places; therefore, altho' in SS a Biſhop and an Elder is of one Order and Authority in Preacl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Word, and Adminiſtring the Sacraments, as <hi>Hierome</hi> doth often confeſs; yet in Government, by ancient uſe of Speech, he is onely called a Biſhop, which is in SS ſo called, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.8. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Chief in Government, to whom the Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Conſecration, by Impoſition of Hands was always principally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; which moſt Ancient Form of Government, when <hi>Arrius</hi> would
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42888:14"/>take away, it was noted among his other Errors.</q> So I hereby truſt it may appear to Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi>'s reproach, and to all their ſhames, that ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any Authority from the Ancient Fathers, to impugne the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and Lawful Calling of Biſhops, not Parſons in every Pariſh, but Biſhops in their Dioceſs and Province, appointed in the Apoſtles times, for the right Order and Government of the Church of Chriſt. As to Biſhop <hi>Spotwood</hi>'s Hiſtory of <hi>Scotland, p.</hi> 514, concerning the Ordination of the Three <hi>Scots</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in King <hi>James</hi>'s time, Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> urged, That it might not be done, becauſe they were not duly made Presbyters, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> by Biſhops; but the Archbiſhop conſidering that this might reflect on the Reformed Churches that had no Biſhops, which was the condition alſo of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Ordination could not be had, it was diſpenſed with. But this is not the Caſe of our Diſſenters, who refuſe Epiſcopal Ordination where it may be had, and ſet up the Presbyterian againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ch.</hi> 5. Begins with the Judicious Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> from whom, after a long Quotation, he infers, <hi>p.</hi> 37. <q>That the Polity in general be neceſſary to the Church;</q> yet it is not neceſſary that any one Temporal Polity be in the SS: This being the Poſition of the <hi>Non-Cons,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> makes this uſe of it: <q>—You cannot ſo much as pretend to this ground, that all the parts of your Diſcipline are in SS; and your Mouths are ſtopt, when you plead againſt all other Forms, ſeeing their Polity may be agreeable to the general Axiomes of SS, as well as yours: And therefore, he ſays, The beſt way for our Cauſe, and the ſtrongeſt againſt them, is to hold, <hi>(as the Non-Cons do)</hi> that in SS there muſt needs be found ſome particular Form of Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which God hath inſtituted, and belongs to all Churches at all times; but by partiality and cunning, to make thoſe things trueſt which are fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to ſerve our purpoſe, is what we neither like, nor mean to follow.</q> In <hi>p.</hi> 38. Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> ſays:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> 
               <q>That in the Clergy there have ever been, and ought to be ſome ſubordinate to others, as the Apoſtles in the beginnig, and to Biſhops ever ſince; as in SS, and all Eccleſiaſtical Records other Miniſters have been.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> 
               <q>That a ſolemn admittance (<hi>viz.</hi> of Miniſters into the Church) is of ſuch neceſſity, that without it there can be no Church Polity.</q> Theſe he ſays are the perpetual and principal parts in Eccleſiaſtical Polity: And this is all that Mr. <hi>J. H.</hi> hath noted out of thoſe Books of Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> which are generally allowed to be genuine; which being not much for his purpoſe, he goes to the Seventh Book, and there he finds this diſcription of a Biſhop: <q>A Biſhop is a Miniſter of God, to whom with permanent continuance, not only a Power of Adminiſtring the Word and Sacraments is given, (which other Presbyters have) but a farther Power to Ordain Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, and a Power of Chiefty in Government over Presbyters as well as Lay-men, a Power to be by way of Juriſdiction a Paſtor, even to Paſtors themſelves.</q> And the things which properly belong to a Biſhop, cannot be common to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Paſtors; and of Biſhops reſtrained to ſome definite local compaſs he ſays, their Regiment we hold to be a thing moſt Divine and Holy in the Church of Chriſt: In two things <hi>J. H.</hi> notes that <hi>Hooker</hi> differs from the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42888:14"/>
               <hi>Non-Cons,</hi> p. 40. 1. They make the Superiority or Priority of Order to be but Temporary; he makes it permanent. 2. They deny the Biſhops have any Power over other Paſtors, that is Mandatory, Judicial, and Coercive, Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> affirms it: Then he ſhews: how Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> reſolves a Sentence of St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> which ſeems inconſiſtent with itſelf: <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>How the Apoſtles ſhould be the Authors of that Government, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> Epiſcopacy, and yet the Cuſtom of the Church be accounted the chief Prop of it.</q> To which the ſubſtance of his Anſwer is, That what Laws the Univerſal Church might change, and doth not, St. <hi>Hierome</hi> aſcribes the continuance of ſuch Laws, tho' inſtituted by God himſelf, to the Judgment of the Church, for they which may abrogate a Law, and do not, may be ſaid to eſtabliſh it; and ſeeing the whole Church receiving it for a Cuſtome, which was eſtabliſhed by them, on whom the Holy Ghoſt was in an abundant manner poured out for ordering of Chriſt's Church, it had either Divine appointment before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, or Divine approbation afterwards. Now how Mr. <hi>J. H.</hi> could from theſe premiſes draw this following concluſion, I cannot perceive, <hi>p.</hi> 44. <q>Let there be, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> as many Biſhopricks, as there are conſiderable Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and a Proviſion made for the Presbyters which are to aſſiſt the Biſhops in the Government of the Churches; and then a Superiority of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop above the Presbyters, will be no longer a Bone of Contention.</q> The Senſe whereof ſeems to me to be this: Let the Presbyters in every Pariſh have all the Power that belongs to Biſhops, and then, and not elſe, they will be pleaſed. But the Judicious <hi>Hooker</hi> would not have been ſo pleaſed with them that ſhould have inferred this concluſion from any premiſes of his. That which followeth our of Mr. <hi>Hooker's</hi> maimed Book, is, 1. That the Church Viſible hath not ordinarily allowed any but Biſhops alone to Ordain; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, in ſome neceſſary Caſes, we may decline from the ordinary ways. 2. That Confirmation hath not always belonged to the Biſhops, but in ſome places, in the abſence of the Biſhop, the Presbyter might Ordain. 3. That the Presbyters are for the moſt part mentioned as Counſellors and Aſſiſtants to the Biſhop.</p>
            <p>The laſt Biſhop whom he would conſtrain to help on his New Model, is Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> who ſays, <hi>That to prevent Diſſention and Confuſion, there muſt needs, even by God's Ordinance, be a Preſident, or Ruler of every Presbytery; but that in the Apoſtles times the Preſidentſhip ſhould go round to every Presbyter by courſe; this is the main point between us.</hi> Then he ſays, <hi>There are Four Things muſt be perpetual in the Church.</hi> 1. <hi>The Diſpenſing of the Word.</hi> And 2. <hi>Sacraments.</hi> 3. <hi>Impoſing of Hands.</hi> 4. <hi>Guiding the Keyes to ſhut or open the Kingdom of God. The firſt Two belong to all Paſtors or Presbyters, but it belongs to ſome ſelected perſons who ſucceed in the Apoſtles places, to moderate the Presbyters of each Church, and to take the ſpecial Charge of Impoſition of Hands. And this ſingularity in ſucceeding, and ſuperiority in ordaining, hath been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from the Apoſtles times, as the peculiar and ſubſiantial Marks of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Power and Calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Power of the Keyes, the private uſe of them in appointing Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, upon the acknowledgement of their ſins, to for bear the Lord's Table
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42888:15"/>for a time, we deny not to Presbyters; but the Biſhop is by Chriſt's own mouth, pronounced to be the Angel of the Church, the chief Steward of his Houſhold, to hear and determine Grievances, with whom the Presbyters ſate at firſt as Aſſeſſors; but when Councils began, only as Beholders and Adviſers of his Judgment; and he adds, that the right by impoſing Hands to Ordain Presbyters and Biſhops, was at firſt derived from the Apoſtles to Biſhops, and not to Presbyters. <hi>N. B.</hi> And for 1500 Years without inſtance or example to the contrary, till this our Age, remained in Biſhops, and not in Presbyters; for which he quotes St. <hi>Hierome: Quid faecit excepta ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Epiſcopus quod non facit Presbyter. J. H.</hi> obſerves, that whereas it is objected, That Impoſition of Hands was by the Presbytery; he anſwers out of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> that by the word Presbytery in SS, muſt be underſtood Biſhops not Presbyters; becauſe Presbyters in the Apoſtles time did not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Hands on a Biſhop. And from this Biſhop he adds, All that we can ſay for Biſhops above Presbyters out of SS is, that the Holy Ghoſt, by the mouth of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> hath given the Biſhop of each place Authority to Ordain the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, to examine ſuch as be faulty, to reprove and diſcharge ſuch as be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, either of unſound Teaching, or offenſive Living; and this he ſaith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to all Biſhops of Chriſt's Church forever. I have tranſcribed ſo much of theſe Quotations, becauſe the very repetition of them is a confutation of that Deſign, which Mr. <hi>H.</hi> attempts, and will ſhew it to be not a healing, but a very hurtful Attempt, as precluding that way of Peace and Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation which is generally intended, if the unreaſonable Demands of ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet Men do not put a bar to it.</p>
            <p>Thus ſaith Mr.<hi>J. H. I have gone through the principal Writers about Church Government in Queen</hi> Elizabeth<hi>'s Reign:</hi> And indeed he hath cull'd out ſuch Foundations on which he would build his Hay and Stubble, as will no way ſuit with them. I ſhall not prepoſſeſs the Reader with the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences which <hi>J. H.</hi> would force from them; but leave every Man to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whether he can fix his Half-ſheet Model on theſe Conceſſions; and now briefly inform the Reader of the Judgment of ſome of theſe Divines, and ſome States-men, what Qualifications he and ſuch Maſter-Builders are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with, for the Building of a Temple fit for the Publick Worſhip of God and our Saviour: And I ſhall begin with,</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <head>The Speech of the Lord Keeper <hi>Puckering</hi> to the Houſe of Lords, by Order of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ESpecially you are commanded by Her Majeſty, to take heed that no ear be given, nor time afforded to the weariſome Sollicitations of thoſe that are commonly called <hi>Puritans,</hi> wherewithal the late Parliament have been exceedingly importuned; which ſort of Men, while in the gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs of their Spirits they labour and ſtrive to advance a new Elderſhip, they do nothing elſe but diſtract the good Repoſe of the Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, which is as well grounded for the body of Religion it ſelf; and as well guided for the Diſcipline, as any Realm that profeſſeth the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42888:15"/>Truth; and as the preſent caſe ſtandeth, it may be doubted, whether they or the Jeſuits offer more danger, or are to be more ſpeedily ſuppreſt; for albeit the Jeſuits do poiſon the Hearts of Her Majeſty's Subjects, under a pretence of Conſcience, they do it but cloſely, and only in corners, but theſe Men do both publiſh in their printed Books, and teach in all their Conventicles, ſundry Opinions, not only dangerous to the well-ſetled State and Policy of the Realm, by putting a Pique between the Clergy and the Laity, but alſo much derogatory to her Sacred Majeſty and her Crown, as well by the diminution of her Ancient and Lawful Revenues, and by denying her Highneſs's Prerogative and Supremacy, as by offering Peril to Her Majeſty's Safety in her own Kingdom; in all which things (however in many other points) they pretend to be at War with the Popiſh Jeſuits, yet by the ſeparation of themſelves from the Unity of their Fellow-Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and by abuſing the Sacred Authority and Majeſty of their Prince, they do both joyn and concur with the Jeſuits in opening the Door, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the way to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Invaſion that is threatned againſt the Realm.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And in the Year 1588, as <hi>Cambden</hi> obſerves in his Annals, the King of <hi>Spain</hi> being thereto encouraged by an Information of the great Diviſions and Animoſities among us, by Reaſon whereof he expected either a greater Party to joyn with him, or a leſs Oppoſition, ſent his Invincible Armado upon our Coaſts; at which time the Proteſtant Diſſenters, inſtead of Arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Defence of the Queen and themſelves, did with greater Importunity and Confidence aſſault her with Petitions and Libels, taking advantage of the Times, as if they were more ready to aſſiſt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> than Her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, in caſe their unreaſonable Requeſts were not granted. As for Biſhop <hi>Jewel,</hi> if he ſaid any thing in their favour, they ill requited him, for on his Preaching a Sermon at St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Croſs,</hi> in defence of the Orders of the Church, and Obedience to them, he was ſo ſpitefully uſed by them, that in his own Vindication, he made a Solemn Proteſtation on his Death-bed, that what he then ſaid, was neither to pleaſe ſome, nor diſpleaſe others, but to promote Peace and Unity among Brethren; of which Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> in his Defence, <hi>p.</hi> 433. ſays, <hi>It is the manner, except you pleaſe their Humour in all things, though you otherwiſe deſerve never ſo well, all is nothing with them, but they will deprave you, rail on you, back-bite you, invent lyes of you, and ſpread falſe rumours, as though you were the vileſt perſons on Earth.</hi> By theſe inſolent proceedings of the Sectaries and Papiſts in Confederacy, the Queen was neceſſitated to paſs thoſe Acts of the 23 and 35 of her Reign, to retain Her Majeſty's Subjects in due Obedience. And this alſo gave oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to that Proclamation of the Queen 1588. againſt Seditious and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Books and Libels.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Royal_proclamation">
               <body>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:42888:16"/>
                  <head>By the QUEEN. A Proclamation againſt certain Seditious and Schiſmatical Books and Libels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Queens moſt Excellent Majeſty, conſidering how within theſe few years paſt, and now of late, certain ſeditious and evil-diſpoſed perſons towards her Majeſty, and the Government eſtabliſhed for cauſes Eccleſiaſtical within her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Dominions, have deviſed, written, printed, or cauſed to be ſeditiouſly and ſecretly publiſhed and diſperſed, ſundry ſchiſmatical and ſeditious Books, diffama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Libels, and other Phanatical Writings amongst her Majeſty's Subjects, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining in them Doctrine very erroneous, and other matters notoriouſly untrue, and ſlanderous to the State, and againſt the Godly Reformation of Religion and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment Eccleſiaſtical eſtabliſhed by Law, and ſo quietly of long time continued, and alſo againſt the perſons of Biſhops, and others placed in Authority Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical under her Highneſs by her Authority, in railing ſort, and beyond the bounds of all good humanity: All which Books, Libels, and Writings, tend by their ſcope to perſwade and bring in a monſtrous and apparent dangerous Innovation within her Dominions and Countries, of all manner of Eccleſiaſtical Government now in uſe, and to the abridging, or rather to the overthrow of her Highneſs lawful Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, allowed by God's Law, and eſtabliſhed by the Laws of the Realm, and conſequently to reverſe, diſſolve, and ſet at liberty the preſent Government of the Church, and to make a dangerous change of the form of Doctrine, and uſe of Divine Service of God, and the Miniſtration of the Sacraments now alſo in uſe, with a raſh and malicious purpoſe alſo to diſſolve the Eſtate of the Prelacy, being one of the three ancient Eſtates of this Realm under her Highneſs, whereof her Majeſty mindeth to have ſuch a reverend regard, as to their places in the Church and Common-wealth appertaineth. All which ſaid lewd and ſeditious practices, do directly tend to the manifeſt wilful breach of great number of good Laws and Statutes of this Realm, inconveniencies nothing regarded by ſuch Innovations.</p>
                  <p>In-conſideration whereof, her Highneſs graciouſly minding to provide ſome good and ſpeedy Remedy to withſtand ſuch notable, dangerous, and ungodly Attempts, and for that purpoſe to have ſuch enormous Malefactors diſcovered and condignly puniſhed, doth ſignifie this her Highneſs miſliking and indignation of ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and wicked Enterprizes; and for that purpoſe doth hereby will and alſo ſtraightly charge and command, that all perſons whatſoever, within any her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Realms and Dominions, who have or hereafter ſhall have any of the ſaid ſeditious Books, Pamphlets, Libels, or Writings, or any of like nature already publiſhed, or hereafter to be publiſhed, in his or their cuſtody, containing ſuch matters as above are mentioned, againſt the preſent Order and Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or the Lawful Miniſters thereof, or againſt the Rites and Ceremonies uſed in the Church, and allowed by the Laws of the Realm: That they and every of them do preſently after, with convenient ſpeed, bring in, and deliver up the ſame unto the Ordinary of the Dioceſs, or of the place where
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42888:16"/>they inhabit, to the intent they may be utterly defaced by the ſaid Ordinary, or otherwiſe uſed by them. And that from henceforth no perſon or perſons whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſo hardy as to write, contrive, print, or cauſe to be publiſhed or diſtributed or to keep any of the ſame, or any other Books, Libels, or Writings of like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and quality, contrary to the true meaning and intent of this her Majeſty's Proclamation. And likewiſe that no man hereafter give any inſtruction, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, favour, or aſſiſtance to the contriving, writing, printing, publiſhing, or diſperſing of the ſame, or ſuch like Books, Libels, or Writings whatſoever, as they tender her Majeſty's good favour, will avoid her high diſpleaſure, and as they will anſwer the contrary at their utmoſt perils: and upon ſuch pains and penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as by the Law any way may be inflicted upon the offenders, in any of theſe behalfs, as perſons maintaining ſuch ſeditious actions, which her Majeſty mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to have ſeverely executed. And if any perſon have had knowledge of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, Writers, Printers, or Diſperſers thereof, which ſhall within one Month after the publication hereof, diſcover the ſame to the Ordinary of the place where he had ſuch knowledge, or to any of her Majeſty's Privy Council: the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall not for his former concealment be hereafter moleſted or troubled. Given at her Majeſty's Palace at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the thirteenth of <hi>February, 1588.</hi> In the One and thirtieth Year of her Highneſs Reign.</p>
                  <closer>GOD SAVE THE QUEEN.</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Arch-biſhop <hi>Grindall</hi> expreſt in a Letter of his, his great fear of two things <hi>(viz.)</hi> Atheiſm and Popery, and both ariſing out of our needleſs Diviſions; by theſe means the Enemies of our Religion gain this, that nothing can be eſtabliſhed by Law in the Proteſtant Religion, whoſe every part is not oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by one or other of her own Profeſſors; ſo that things continuing looſe and confuſed, the Papiſts have their Opportunity to urge their way, which is attended with Order and Government. And our Religion continuing thus diſtracted and divided, ſome vile wretches lay hold on the Argument on one ſide to confute the other, and ſo at laſt to deſtroy all. And it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Life of Mr. <hi>Hooker, p.</hi> 9. they perſwaded men to believe that the Biſhops were <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt</hi> was to be deſtroyed by the Sword; and beginning with Petitions, they proceeded to Admonitions, then to Remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances, then to numbring their Party, then to that boldneſs, that one told the Queen in a Sermon, <hi>She was like an untamed Heifer, that would not be ruled by God's people, but obſtructed his Diſcipline.</hi> And we have heard and ſeen worſe things in our days.</p>
            <p>Arch-biſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> in his Defence of the Anſwer to <hi>T. C. p.</hi> 605. tells the Puritans, <q>That the Papiſts could not have met with better Proctors than they. And 55. That they did the Pope very good Service, and that he would not miſs them for any thing: for what is his deſire, but to have this Church of <hi>England,</hi> which he hath accurſed, utterly defaced and diſcredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to have it by any means overthrown, if not by Foreign means, yet by Domeſtical Diſſention. And what fitter Inſtruments could he have had for that purpoſe, who under pretence of Zeal overthrow that which other men
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42888:17"/>have builded; under colour of Purity, ſeek to bring in Deformity; and under the Cloak of Equality and Humility, would uſurp as great Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and lofty Lordlineſs over their Pariſhes, as ever the Pope did over the whole Church, and that they were made the Engines of the <hi>Roman</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave, whereby they intend to overthrow this Church even by theſe mens Folly, which they could not compaſs by all their Policy.</q> The Epiſtle of the Arch-biſhop to the Reader, before his Defence of the Anſwer to <hi>T. C</hi>'s Admonition, is worth pernſal.</p>
            <p>As for Biſhop <hi>Bancroft,</hi> the whole deſign of his Book is to manifeſt what diſturbance the endeavours of the Presbyterians to eſtabliſh their Elderſhip, did create in the Nation by ſuch dangerous Poſitions and Practices, as were in his time with equal violence and malice carried on for the deſtruction of the Church, as it was then eſtabliſhed. There are ſome other of the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Divines, whoſe Writings I have not, nor is there need to enquire far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into them, ſeeing there is nothing alledged from them by Mr. <hi>J. H.</hi> but what being compared with their other ſayings and practices doth fully fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate his deſigns. And when the Biſhops of our Church do ſo ingenuouſly mention all that may be ſaid for their Adverſaries, with ſo much Veracity, Candor, and Moderation, what a Reproach is it to their Opponents, to deal with them with ſo much Scorn and Contempt, ſuch Bitterneſs and Paſſion, ſuch Slanders and Falſhoods, as too many do, and as <hi>T. C.</hi> did with the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> whom Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> called her <hi>black Husband,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held him againſt the Contrivances and contrary Deſigns of <hi>Lecheſter,</hi> and thoſe Conformiſts whom he favoured, to promote his own Sacrilegious ends.</p>
            <p>As for Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> whom Biſhop <hi>King</hi> calls <hi>Malleum Hereticorum,</hi> who was as meek and modeſt a man, as well as judicious, as any in his Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he did profeſs to the Arch-biſhop, <hi>See p.</hi> 17. <hi>of his Life,</hi> 
               <q>That he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved his Adverſary, Mr. <hi>Travers.</hi> to be a good man, and that occaſioned him to examine his own Conſcience concerning his Opinions, and to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that, he conſulted the Holy Scripture and other Laws Humane and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, whether the Conſcience of him, and others of his judgment, ought ſo far to be complyed with, as to alter the frame of Church-Government, and manner of Worſhip and Ceremonies as oft as their tender Conſciences ſhall require it; in which examination he had not only ſatisfied himſelf, but begun his Eccleſiaſtical Polity for the ſatisfaction of others, which he juſtly calls, a Demonſtration of the Reaſonableneſs of our Eccleſiaſtical Laws, and a hopeful Foundation for the Churches Peace, and not to provoke either Mr. <hi>T. C.</hi> the Arch-biſhop's Adverſary, nor Mr. <hi>Travers,</hi> whom, ſaith Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> I take to be mine (not mine Enemy) God knows this to be my meaning.</q> Yet his Adverſaries that could not anſwer his Arguments, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived to blot his Reputation, and accuſed him of Incontinency, which by a Trepan, as the Author of his Life relates, <hi>p.</hi> 22. they endeavoured to faſten on him; he kept this Grief to himſelf many Months, with great anxiety, until he revealed it to Mr. <hi>Edwin Sands</hi> and <hi>George Cranmer,</hi> who had been his Pupils, who enquiring into the Impoſture, ſo followed it, that they brought his Accuſers to open Confeſſion and Puniſhment, which Puniſhment he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42888:17"/>endeavoured to prevent, but was denied; at which he replyed, <hi>That how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he would Faſt and Pray, that God would give them Repentance, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to undergo their Puniſhment;</hi> and the firſt part was granted, if we may believe, ſaith my Author, the penitent Behaviour, and open Confeſſion of his Accuſer.</p>
            <p>How his Adverſaries dealt with his Books after his Death, is thus related. That one Mr. <hi>Clark</hi> and another Miniſter deſired of his Widow a Month after his Death to ſearch his Study for ſome Papers, wherof they burnt ſome, and tore others; but Dr. <hi>Jackſon</hi> having tranſcribed ſome draught of his three laſt Books, they were compleated by Dr. <hi>Spencer,</hi> who was acquainted with the Deſign of thoſe Books. The Doctor left them with Dr. <hi>King,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Londo,</hi> and he to his Son, Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> he to Dr. <hi>Abbot,</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in whoſe Library they continued till the Death of Arch-biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> and then the Library was given to <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> for his good Services, and then many alterations and additions were made in them, to make them ſpeak for the power of the People above the King, for which, when the Lord <hi>Say</hi> quoted <hi>Hooker</hi>'s Authority to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, he replyed, <hi>That the Books were not</hi> Hooker's; <hi>but however he would conſent to what was propoſed out of thoſe doubted Books, if that Lord would conſent to Mr.</hi> Hooker<hi>'s Judgment in thoſe Books which were undoubted.</hi> The ſame may I ſay concerning the Judgment of ſuch Divines as Mr. <hi>J. H.</hi> hath quoted, we will ſtand to what is but weakly and impertinently quoted from thoſe Divines, if they will ſtand to what is more maturely and pertinently by them alledged and proved, agreeably alſo to their own practice for Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan Epiſcopacy, as eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If thoſe Diſſenters who were ſo importunate and induſtrious to advance their Diſcipline on the ruines of the eſtabliſhed Church, had proceeded on the Principles laid down by the Divines above-mentioned, whereof this is one that they lay hold on <hi>(viz.) That the forms of Government not being plainly expreſt in Scripture, are alterable, and may by the Authority of the Civil Magiſtrate be determined to this or that ſpecies</hi> (which yet they will not grant of their own Diſcipline) <hi>they ought then to acquieſce in that Government which was eſtabliſhed, and to which all thoſe Divines moſt willingly ſubmitted, as the beſt in all the Chriſtian World; and though by reaſon of their diſſent from it, they had drawn on themſelves the execution of ſome moderate Penalties, yet if they had been fully perſwaded that they did ſuffer for a good Conſcience, and for Righteouſneſs ſake, they ought like good Chriſtians to have taken it pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, and not by Railing, by Sedition, by forming Schiſms, and meditating Rebellions, ſeek to avenge themſelves, and return evil for evil, but contrarily bleſſing, being thereto called by the Example and Precepts of their great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; but when they returned evil for good, and hatred for good-will, and thought themſelves perſecuted, becauſe they could not graſp a Power to perſecute their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours; this was not agreeable to that wiſdom that comes from above, which is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be intreated.</hi> And if our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſſenters be ſatisfied of the purity of our Doctrine, they may by the Principles which are laid down, ſubmit to that Diſcipline and Government
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42888:18"/>that Authority doth eſtabliſh, there being nothing in it contrary to the Word of God, but wholly agreeable to the conſtant practice of the Univerſal Church.</p>
            <p>I think it ſufficient to ſolve all that hath been alledged out of our Divines to clear theſe two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What kind of Government was ſetled by the Apoſtles.</item>
               <item>2. What Anſwer may be given to the Objections ſo often mentioned from St. <hi>Hierom.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>As to the firſt, it is evident, that there was a Superiority in the Apoſtles to thoſe to whom they committed the care of the ſeveral Churches, whether they were Biſhops or Presbyters; and as the Apoſtles dyed, their Succeſſors in Eccleſiaſtical Power, who in all Ages were the Biſhops, were the Subjects of that Superiority; ſuch as <hi>Timothy, Titus, Clemen, Linus, &amp;c.</hi> and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors as they ſtand recorded in Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory; for what the Apoſtles did for the perpetual Order and Government of the Church, was agreeable to our Saviour's Inſtitution, and all Antiquity bears proof to this Truth, that from the Apoſtles days there were ſetled in the moſt eminent Churches of <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Rome, Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> ſeveral Biſhops that had a Superiority over the Presbyters, in their reſpective Churches, and that the three Orders of Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, were eſtabliſhed in thoſe Churches in thoſe pureſt and moſt Primitive times; inſomuch that they who will not admit thoſe Teſtimonies, will be to ſeek for one of the beſt Proofs for the Canon of the Scripture. As therefore we believe the Succeſſion of <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours from the Writings of ſuch Hiſtorians as lived near their times, ſo may we believe the truth of ſuch Orders of Men, and of their Succeſſions, as it is delivered by Men of good Credit and Honeſty, that lived near thoſe times, and have handed down in undoubted written Records, from Age to Age, St. <hi>Polycarp, Ignatius, Clemens,</hi> who converſed with the Apoſtles; <hi>Ireneus, Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and others, that lived with them; then <hi>Origen, Clem. Alexandrinus, Tertullian,</hi> who ſucceeded them, and many others, who lived within two hundred years after the Apoſtles, from whom <hi>Euſebius</hi> had the Materials of his Hiſtory, and refers to them for the truth of his Relations.</p>
            <p>He had the Acts of the Martyrs, and the Books of <hi>Hegeſippus,</hi> concerning the Acts of the Church; from which, and other helps, from the very Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of the Chriſtians, he compiled his Hiſtory, and particularly the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Biſhops. <hi>Clemens Rom.</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſpeaks of the Officers of the Church in his time, alluding to thoſe under the Law: The High-Prieſt hath his Office, the Prieſt his Station, and the Levite his Miniſtry, the Lay-man his Office; let every one worſhip God in his Order. <hi>Ignatius</hi> mentions theſe Three Orders in his Epiſtles ſo plainly, that the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of thoſe Orders have martyred him again in his Reputation, denying his Epiſtles to be genuine, which the Learned Biſhop <hi>Pearſon</hi> hath irrefraga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly aſſerted; and ſo hath Dr. <hi>Beveridge</hi> the Authority of Apoſtolical Canons, which have been owned by the Councils, and expreſly aſſert the Three Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; ſo that tho' while the Apoſtles lived the Names might be confounded, yet immediately on their deaths, all Ancient Writers have diſtinguiſhed them;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42888:18"/>becauſe ſuch as ſucceeded to their Power were Biſhops; and yet all the Miniſter's or Elders were not ſo, for a Parity is uſually the Parent of Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and if ſuch a Parity had been ſetled by Chriſt or his Apoſtles, how could it be, that as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſays, <hi>The whole World ſhould agree for prevention of Schiſm, to alter what Chriſt had eſtabliſhed:</hi> Was the whole World <hi>(i. e.)</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular Church (which are it ſeems agreed on ſetting up a Biſhop above Presbyters) wiſer than our Saviour; or had they Authority ſo to do? And if they did ſo by ſufficient Authority, why will the Presbyters as gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally agree to pull them down now, as their Ancients did to ſet them up? So that I ſee no ſhadow of Reaſon, why we may not ſubſcribe to that which is ſaid before the Book of Conſecration, <hi>That it is evident to all Men diligently reading the Holy Scripture, and Ancient Authors, that from the Apoſtles time, there have been ever theſe Orders of Miniſters in the Church, Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As to St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s Teſtimony, the import of it is this, That tho' the Apoſtles had a Superiority over Presbyters, yet when they died they did not bequeath that Power to others, but left it in common to the Presbyters, whoſe management of it was ſuch, as it begat Schiſms and Animoſities; for ſuppreſſion of which it was thought fit through the whole World, to chuſe out of the body of the Presbyters, one that ſhould have a Preſidency over the reſt; ſo that this Preſidency was not an Apoſtolical Inſtitution, but Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical and Prudential Conſtitution, wherein St. <hi>Hierom</hi> doth not only contradict the Joynt Suffrage of all the Ancients, but his own Teſtimony. Againſt this Opinion of St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſome affirm, that what he ſaid was in a Diſcourſe againſt ſome proud Deacons, that would equal themſelves with the Presbyters, which was as great a preſumption as to invade the Office of the Biſhops, ſeeing in moſt things (as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſays) the Biſhops and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were of the ſame Power; for, <hi>Quis patiatur,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Hierom, &amp;c.</hi> Who can endure that they whoſe Office it was to attend on Tables and Widows, ſhould equal themſelves to thoſe, at whoſe Prayers the Body and Blood of Chriſt is conſecrated. But to let this paſs, I ſay, 2. This Opinion of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects on our Saviour and his Apoſtles, as if they had not ſufficiently provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the future Peace of the Church; and that if the Presbyters in after-Ages had not been more provident, the Church would have wanted a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt Schiſms: And if ſuch a Remedy were thought neceſſary by the whole World, (of Presbyters) then is the Office of a Biſhop founded on Natural Reaſon, for it is moſt true that the Peace of the Church (which conſiſts of a great number of the Clergy, which are as ſubject to Paſſions as other Men) cannot be ſecured in St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s Opinion, without a Superior Power over them: <hi>Cui ſi non exors &amp; ab omnibus eminens detur poteſtas tot in Eccleſiis efficientur Schiſmata quot Sacerdotes:</hi> To which, if all the reſt of the Clergy do not yield Obedience, there may be as many Schiſms in the Church as there are Prieſts. And thus it would follow, that neither Chriſt nor his Apoſtles did provide ſo well for the Churches Peace, as common Prudence, and Natural Reaſon would direct.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:42888:19"/>
            <p n="3">3. It being granted there was a Superiority in the Apoſtles, it is alledged, That after their Deaths, the Government, for a long time, fell to the ſeveral Presbyters, until the inconveniency of it appeared by the increaſe of Schiſms; and then it was agreed, <hi>Toto orbe,</hi> through the whole World, to advance one Presbyter with Power over the reſt. But when the Succeſſion of Biſhops is apparently recorded in moſt of the eminent Churches, immediately after the deceaſe of the Apoſtles, it is an incredible ſtory to tell us, that the Power of Governing the Church was in the Body of the Presbyters, of which there is not the leaſt Teſtimony in Antiquity for any one Church, nor any for the Time, Place, or Perſons, when this <hi>Toto orbe decretum,</hi> this new alteration ſhould be made; nor is it probable that all the World would agree at once to make an alteration in Church-Government; ſo that the reſult is this: There was a Superiority in the Apoſtles days, which ceaſed for a while, and then the Presbyters raiſed in common; but that Rule or Government was found to be the occaſion of many Schiſms, and then the Apoſtolical Superio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was decreed by all to be Re-eſtabliſhed. 4. St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s words do not conſiſt with themſelves; for when he ſays theſe Presbyters did exalt one choſen from among themſelves, to a higher degree, whom they named a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, how can that conſiſt with what immediately follows: That a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had not the Power of Ordaining. <hi>Quid enim facit exceptâ Ordinatione Epiſcopus quod non faciat Presbiter:</hi> It ſeems by this the ancient Presbyters did firſt for neceſſary Cauſes, firſt ſet up Biſhops, and then it will ſound ill if our new Presbyters ſhould put them down, unneceſſarily. So that the moſt of what hath been alledged from the Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in favour of Mr. <hi>J. H</hi>'s New Model, depending on the Teſtimony of St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom,</hi> and that being proved to be a ſingle and ſlender Opinion, contrary to the Practice of all Churches, and not conſiſtent with itſelf: I ſuppoſe the Reader will not be of Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s mind, to deſtroy the eſtabliſhed Conſtitution, for a new, dangerous, and impracticable Invention, which indeed was no elder then <hi>Socinus,</hi> the firſt Inventer of Independent Churches, granting to every Congregation a Power to Elect their Church-Officers for Governing their Affairs, and deciding of Controverſies. And by this Deſign I perceive Mr. <hi>J. H.</hi> is of the ſame Judgment with Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> as well in Church-Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, as in Doctrine, whoſe Treatiſe of <hi>The In-dwelling of the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Praying by the Spirit,</hi> (not without a Contempt of our Lord's Prayer) Mr. <hi>J. H.</hi> in his peaceable Diſquiſitions and Animadverſions on a Diſcourſe writ againſt Dr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s book of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> he attempts to reconcile to the Truth, as now he doth the Independent Principles and Practices with the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. line 2. after the word <hi>Controverſie,</hi> add <hi>the Leſs is bleſſed of the Greater.</hi> P. 4. l. 35, for <hi>of</hi> read <hi>or.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
